<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The life of Oliver Cromwel, Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland being an account of all the battles, sieges, and other military atchievements, wherein he was engaged, in these three nations : and likewise, of his civil administrations while he had the supream government, till his death.</title>
            <author>R. B., 1632?-1725?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35243</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC T135016</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12123974</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12123974</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54496</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35243)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54496)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 90:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The life of Oliver Cromwel, Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland being an account of all the battles, sieges, and other military atchievements, wherein he was engaged, in these three nations : and likewise, of his civil administrations while he had the supream government, till his death.</title>
                  <author>R. B., 1632?-1725?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 137, [7] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by D. Pratt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1680?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Nathaniel Crouch [i.e. R.B.]. Cf. Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Advertisements ([7] p.) at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:54496:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <p>The EFFIGEY of OLIVER CROMWEL, Late Lord-Protector of ENGLAND.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54496:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>LIFE</hi> OF <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> Lord PROTECTOR Of the Common-Wealth Of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being an Account of all the Battles, Sieges, and other Military Atchievements, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was engaged, in theſe Three Nations.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe, of his Civil Adminiſtrations, while he had the Supream Government, till his Death.</p>
            <p>Relating Matter of Fact, without Partiality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by D. PRATT, at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Crown,</hi> over-againſt <hi>York-Houſe,</hi> in the <hi>Strand.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:54496:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54496:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THERE is ſcarce a Character of any Man of Fame in the World, which ſuffers ſuch an unaccountable Variety, as this, of <hi>Oliver Cromwel.</hi> His Hiſtory is told ſo many Ways, and ſo every way different from one another, that it will be impoſſible for Poſterity to make a right Judgment of him, or of his Accounts.</p>
            <p>On one hand he is repreſented as a <hi>Hero,</hi> on the other as a <hi>Traytor;</hi> on the one hand he is called the greateſt <hi>Soldier,</hi> on the other the greateſt <hi>Villain</hi> of the Age he liv'd in; on one ſide he is the greateſt <hi>Polititian,</hi> on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the greateſt <hi>Hypocrite;</hi> on one ſide the greateſt <hi>General,</hi> on the other the greateſt <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant;</hi> but I muſt add, that both ſides agree, that he was what ever they add to it, not <hi>Great</hi> only, but the <hi>Greateſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Word, <hi>Party</hi> is the Teſt of his Hiſtory, if a <hi>Cavalier</hi> writes Hiſtory we know what to expect of him <hi>(viz.)</hi> that <hi>Oliver</hi> ſhall be villi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd with the utmoſt Spleen and Rage: If a <hi>Round-head,</hi> he ſhall be exalted with the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Rhetorick. However to ſpeak Impartially, the <hi>Cavalier's</hi> will acknowledge this, namely, that he was a great Man, and will often ſay
<pb facs="tcp:54496:3"/>what great Things he has done, and how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py it had been, if he had been on the King's ſide: And on the contrary, the <hi>Presbyterian's</hi> will ſay on all Occaſions, how glorious a Man had he been, if he had but done <hi>So</hi> and <hi>So? (viz.)</hi> if he had but turn'd out the <hi>P.</hi> ſet him up and the like.</p>
            <p>To do his Character Juſtice, two Actions fully'd it in general, namely, cutting off the King, and ſetting himſelf up as Head of the Common-wealth; in the first he dipp'd his hands in a cold Murder on the Perſon of his Sovereign; and in the ſecond he darken'd all the Glory of his Gallantry, and of the great Things he had done in the Field, ſhewing that it was all with a ſecret Aim to gratify his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Ambition.</p>
            <p>Abſtracted from theſe, Character was truly Great, and 'tis among ſuch as are ſcarce to be imitated in the World; this was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by his worſt Enemies. The whole is Elegantly expreſs'd in two Lines by that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Poet Mr. <hi>Melvell.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Tho' his Government did a <hi>Tyrant</hi> reſemble,</l>
               <l>He made <hi>England</hi> great &amp; her Enemy's tremble.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But I return to his Hiſtory, and ſhall give a Brief but Sure and Impartial Draft of, with all poſſible Partiallity.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biography">
            <pb facs="tcp:54496:3"/>
            <head>THE LIFE of <hi>Oliver Cromwel,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>LIVER CROMWEL</hi> was born at <hi>Huntington,</hi> deſcended of the ancient Family of the <hi>Williams's,</hi> of the County of <hi>Glamorgan;</hi> and by Adoption into that of the <hi>Cromwels,</hi> the more noble Family, as deſcend of <hi>Thomas Cromwel,</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> the Ax that hew'd down the Abbeys in the Time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight.</p>
            <p>His Education, in his Youth, was, for a Time, at the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where, though he attained to no great Perfection in Learning, yet, with his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Additionals, the Fox's Tail with the Lion's Skin, his Strength of Reaſon with the ſharp Edge of his Sword, ſtood him in great Stead in his After-tranfactions; and which, together with his indefati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable Induſtry, render'd him ſo fortunate,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54496:4"/>that he never fell ſhort of what he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took.</p>
            <p>After his Return from the Univerſity, without any extraordinary Reſpects from the Muſes, whoſe Unkindneſs he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards moſt ſeverely retaliated, he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for the Future, upon the firſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, to try the Fortune of <hi>Mars;</hi> but long it was ere the blind Goddeſs provid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him any Action; during which Time he married a Gentlewoman of the ancient Family of the <hi>Bourchiers,</hi> (whence the Earls of <hi>Eſſex</hi> were deſcended) by whom he had two Sons that ſurvived him, <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> and <hi>Henry,</hi> and three Daughters, <hi>Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get, Mary,</hi> and <hi>Frances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For his private Fortunes they were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, a Mediocrity betwixt Riches and Poverty; the one blunting the Edge of Wit and Induſtry, the other, by its Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, whetting it quite away. But what was wanting in his Eſtate, was ſupplied in the greatneſs of his Mind, which put him upon high Attemps, which proved ſo ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful, that at laſt they placed him at the Helm of Government.</p>
            <p>He took his firſt Riſe from the long Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, where he was a Member, being choſen Burgeſs for the Univerſity of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge;</hi> in this Parliament that Fire burſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54496:4"/>forth, which had been long before in kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that fatal Diviſion betwixt King and Parliament; with which laſt he wholly ſided: What Motives induced him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, I know not, nor will I determine of the Integrity of his Choice; this I am ſure of, he took the more fortunate, or, by his Manhood, made it ſo.</p>
            <p>When he delivered his Mind in the Houſe, it was with a ſtrong and maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line Eloquence, more able to perſwade than to be perſwaded; his Expreſſions were hardy; Opinions reſolute; Aſſeverations grave and vehement, always intermixt, <hi>Andronicus</hi> like, with Sentences of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to give them the greater Weight, and the better to inſinuate into the Affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the People, he expreſſed himſelf with ſome kind of Paſſon, but with ſuch a commanding wiſe Deportment, that at his Pleaſure he governed and ſwayed the Houſe, as he had moſt Times the leading Voice.</p>
            <p>Thoſe who find no ſuch Wonders in his Speeches, may find it in the Effect of them; moſt of the People he was concerned in, being, as they term it, Enemies to Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learning; and whoſoever ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, with an eloquent Oration, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe go about to reconcile them, and make
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54496:5"/>Friends, ſhould make them Enemies; ſuch great Adorers are they of the Scripture Phraſe, though but little Practicer's; ſuch as our late Times have brought forth. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he uſurp'd his holy Oil Quotations very frequently, which were ſo advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to his Deſigns, that <hi>Cicero</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſthenes,</hi> with all their Troops and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, could never have ſo perſwaded and moved the People, as he with one Text of Scripture aptly applied; the Dove, and the Serpent, of Scripture, and ſome ſmall Parcel of Policy, to what he intended, ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intermixed.</p>
            <p>But his Side ſtanding more in need of Action then Eloquence, he quitted the Houſe, and betook him to the Field, to manifeſt his Courage as well as his Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, maintain by his Deeds what his Words had introduced.</p>
            <p>Having raiſed a Troop of Horſe at his own Coſts and Charges, he marched a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Muſes to <hi>Cambridge,</hi> (whereof he was Burges) ſeizing on a very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sum of Money and Plate, which the Colleges had raiſed, and were ſending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way unto <hi>Oxford;</hi> which, as it was very advantageous to his own Side, (Money be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the very Liſe and Sinews of War) ſo did it much weaken the adverſe Party,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54496:5"/>who had always great Want of it. The Parliament having on their Side the rich City of <hi>London,</hi> that inexhauſtible Bank of Treaſure. By this Means he ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened himſelf with ſufficient Aids to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Lord <hi>Capel,</hi> who was to have been ſeconded by Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> and ſhould have ſeized on <hi>Cambridge,</hi> thereby to have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peded the Aſſociation of the adjoining Counties for the Parliament.</p>
            <p>He being advanced from a Captain to a Colonel, having compleated a Regiment of Horſe, to the full Number of a thouſand Men, in the Spring of the Year he marches to <hi>Lowerſtoft</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> where he ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurprized Sir <hi>Thomas Barker,</hi> Sir <hi>John Pettas</hi> his Brother, with above twenty o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſons of Note, who were entring into an Aſſociation for the King; ſeveral Peaſons of Quality, and divers Noblemen hourly flocking to that Rendezvouz; this other Service was very ſeaſonably render'd to the Parliament, the King's Party both in <hi>Suffolk</hi> and <hi>Norfolk,</hi> being much diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged by this Succeſs.</p>
            <p>Having, by new raiſed Aids, inforced his Army to a very conſiderable Strength, he marched into <hi>Lincolnſhire,</hi> with a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to aſſiſt thoſe Forces that lay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Newark,</hi> a very ſtrong and ſtout Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54496:6"/>of the King's; where, by their daily Excurſions they kept all the Country thereabouts in awe; which he not only block'd up, but alſo defeated part of the Earl of <hi>Newcaſtle</hi>'s Army which came to relieve them. I ſhall not need to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larize all his Actions, his other interveen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Atchievements are innumerable. To look forwards, only to mention the Battle of <hi>Marſton Moor,</hi> where by his Valour he turn'd the Scales of Victory, which at the firſt enclined to the King's Side: As alſo, at that fatal Fight at <hi>Naſeby,</hi> where the King's Foot were all cut in Pieces, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoners: His memorable Diſcomfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the King's Forces at <hi>Preſton,</hi> in <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire,</hi> over Duke <hi>Hamilton</hi> and Sir <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maduke Langdale;</hi> the laſt of them as vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly faithful to the King, as the other was diſloyal: Their united Forces amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Twenty five thouſand, his not above Ten thouſand at moſt; (altho' indeed he found little Oppoſition, ſave only of thoſe few Forces of Sir <hi>Marmaduke Langdale,</hi> who fought it out courageouſly to the laſt Man.) Should I thus continue to ſignalize his Trophies, I might tire out the Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er with his ſtrange Succeſſes; let it ſuffice then, that his Actions, with ſuch Fame, arrived at the Houſe, that in Recompence,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54496:6"/>they firſt beſtowed on him the General<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the Horſe, and afterwards the Lieutenant Generalſhip of the whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Certainly if his Ambition had ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated here, and his wonderful Succeſſes had not raiſed his Thoughts higher; if he could not, for his Martial Merits, have been beloved, he had Power enough to have render'd himſelf ſave, and for his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Atchievements, fear'd, honour'd and admir'd.</p>
            <p>Raiſed to this Degree of Command, he was more careful of hazarding his Perſon than before; well knowing the Loſs of a General is the moſt irreparable of all Loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; for him to expoſe his Perſon to trivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Hazards, in the Breath of whoſe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils the victorious Atchievements of the Soldiers remains, is too impertinently ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturous, as if it were more glorious to fight than command: Whereas, that is more eſpecially the Virtue of a common Soldier: This other of a Leader, whoſe principal Talent lies more in Direction than Execution; more in the Brain than Hand: Thus that ever to be deplored Laureat of our Times, the Gentleman of the long Robe, the Oracle of the King's Couſels, the Lord <hi>Faukland,</hi> was as unfortunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54496:7"/>loſt, as unneceſſarily engaged in the Field.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, he grew ſo ſubtilly care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as to maintain a fair Correſpondence; there was no Place taken; no Battle won, but he was the firſt that brought or ſent Word to the Houſe; by which he inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated himſelf into the Affections both of the Parliament and People; expreſſing his own Actions in ſuch Terms, as whilſt he ſeemingly attributed much to others, he drew the whole Commendation thereof to himſelf.</p>
            <p>One Thing that made his Brigade ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible, was his arming them ſo well, as whilſt they aſſured themſelves they could not be overcome, it aſſured him to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their Enemies. He himſelf, as they call'd him <hi>Ironſide,</hi> needed not to be aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of a Nick-name that ſo often ſaved his Life.</p>
            <p>Theſe were his Acts whilſt Lieutenant General, by which he got ſo great a Name in War, as <hi>Eſſex, Waller,</hi> and thoſe other great Names before him, excepting only Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi>'s Laurels, which were interwoven with his, the reſt were ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up in his moſt inimitable Succeſſes, even as great Rivers are ſwallowed up by the Ocean.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:54496:7"/>
For the reſt of his Actions when he was General; his conquering <hi>Ireland;</hi> his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing <hi>Scotland;</hi> the many other Battles he fought till his ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhing the War in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> To treat alſo largely of theſe it's Trophies, would weary the Pen of a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, though induſtrious Writer, that ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerns the Incivility of thoſe late Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil War, howſoever they were ſtrange Succeſſes, and ſo many, that as a Modern Poet agrees with what I have expreſſed;
<q>
                  <l>—It were a Work ſo great,</l>
                  <l>Would make <hi>Olympus</hi> bearing <hi>Atlas</hi> ſweat.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore ſummarily relate the moſt notable Occurrences then happening, leaving the leſs Aſſairs to be related by more voluminous Authors.</p>
            <p>No ſooner were the Civil Wars of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> terminated, by the Diſcomfiture of all the King's Armics; the taking of his own Perſon, and putting him to Death, but the Parliament, by a ſolemn Vote and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, changed the Monarchial Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, into a Commonwealth. The King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> diſcontented at this Change, uniting themſelves, owned the late King's eldeſt Son, and ſolemnly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed him King; no Place conſiderable ſtanding out for the Parliament, ſaving on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Dublin</hi> and <hi>London-derry;</hi> the firſt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54496:8"/>of was immediately beſieged by an Army of Twenty two thouſand Men, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond;</hi> and the other by a conſiderable Party of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the Country. To the reducing of this Kingdom was <hi>Oliver Cromwel</hi> nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Governour of Ireland</hi> by the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; who, with a well apointed Army ſet ſail for <hi>Dublin:</hi> Where, although he found Things in an indifferent good Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond</hi> having been beaten off, by the Valour of <hi>Michael Jones</hi> the Governour, yet he met with Work e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for his Army: For <hi>Droghedah,</hi> one one of the beſt and conſiderableſt Places in all <hi>Ireland,</hi> held out ſtifly againſt them, and having a ſtrong Party, bid Defiance to his Army: Yet notwithſtanding, after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Aſſaults, and much Valour ſhewn on both Sides, he at laſt took it, putting therein to death 3000 <hi>Iriſh;</hi> who, tho' E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomies, yet for their Valour and undaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reſolution, might have been look'd on with a more merciful Eye, as they were Men, and more eſpecially Chriſtians. Soon after followed the Surrender of <hi>Trim, Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalke, Nury, Wexford, Rove, Bandonbridge,</hi> and <hi>Kingſale;</hi> yet notwithſtanding the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of theſe Towns, many of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> retreating to their Bogs and inacceſſible
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:54496:8"/>Places, held out for a long Time, in dſepite of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To proceed, not only the <hi>Iriſh</hi> ſhew'd their Diſlike of this Change of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but alſo the Colonies in <hi>Virginia,</hi> and the <hi>Carybde Iſlands;</hi> to the reducing of whom the Parliament ſent Sir <hi>George As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kue,</hi> with a Fleet of Ships, who brought them again into Obedience.</p>
            <p>In the mean Time the <hi>Scots</hi> were very buſie, they had commenced a Treaty with Prince <hi>Charles</hi> at <hi>Breda,</hi> which at laſt was concluded on, he aſſenting to their Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government; and they to inſtal and re-eſtabliſh him in that Kingdom, and in the other accordingly, as they queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned not but Fortune would anſwer their blind zealous Covenant Expectations.</p>
            <p>The Prince puts forth to Sea, and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpite of foul Weather, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> King Fiſhers that lay there to intercept him, he landed ſafely at the <hi>Spey.</hi> in the North of <hi>Scotland.</hi> Now, tho' the <hi>Scots</hi> had a King, yet (as if they had none) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one did that which is right in his own Eyes; and, as if they intended him only the Title, being now in their Power, they forced him to follow the Rules of their haughty Clergy, in all their ſanatick Humours and imperious Decrees. Firſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54496:9"/>then, they bereaved him of all his old Friends, Counſellors, and Confederates, whether of the Clergy or Laity, as thoſe who adhered to Epiſcopal Government, and ſo not pure enough for ſo reform'd a People. Thus they hamſtringed him, not as what was formerly in the Sign-poſt, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of printed Papers. Next, they make him take the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> that ſtrange Fire which the <hi>Scots</hi> believe deſcended from Heaven, and by which they, at their Pleaſures, kindle thoſe Wars wherewith they infeſt <hi>England:</hi> Then theſe Horſe Farriers of the Conſcience gave him another Drench, he is taught to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Sins of his Father's Houſe, and of his own, the Idolatry of his Mother, by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant adhering to the Cauſe of God, according to the Covenant, in the firm Eſtabliſhment of Church Government, as it is laid down in the Directory for publick Worſhip, Confeſſion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith and Catechiſm.</hi> Theſe, with divers others of the like Nature, they wrought ſo on his Neceſſity, they obtruded, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rammed into his Conſcience (although with much Reluctancy) he ſigned to, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many ſtrange Faces at theſe bitter Pills he ſwallowed, yet it better'd not his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which was like that of a Child un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Tutors and Governors; there was not
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54496:9"/>an Officer in that Kirk or Commonwealth how vile and abject ſoever, in Place or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but enjoyed more Freedom both in Body and Mind, than he. Guarded in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed he was, but no otherwiſe than he was ſurrounded with the <hi>Ignis Fatuus</hi> of their zealous Suſpicions of him, ſo that move he muſt not but in the Sphere of the Kirk, their <hi>Primum mobile;</hi> whereby 'tis apparent, that the Government of that Nation might be almoſt queſtion'd whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ever were truly Monarchial (tho' they had Kings.)</p>
            <p>To proceed, the Parliament having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of all their Proceedings, recalled Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Cromwel</hi> out of <hi>Ireland,</hi> making him <hi>Generaliſſimo</hi> of the Commonwealths Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, in the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi>'s Stead, who at the ſame Time laid down his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; he, with a choice Army, marches into <hi>Scotland,</hi> and after many petty Defeats, gives them a great Overthrow at <hi>Dumbar, September</hi> 3, 1650, and proſecuting his Victory, takes <hi>Leith,</hi> a very conſiderable and advantageous Place; as alſo <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> the Metropolitan City of all <hi>Scotland.</hi> Thus he ſet firm there his Sword, hewing his Way for him to conquer that Country, which the King loſt by his Pen.</p>
            <p>Now were the <hi>Scots</hi> truly miſerable, for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:54496:10"/>beſides a raging Enemy in the very Heart of their Kingdom, they were divided among themſelves, even to the killing and ſlaying of one another; one Party in the North was for the King without the Kirk; another. Party in the Weſt, was for the Kirk without the King; a third Party was for the King and Kirk. Yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Loſſes and Diviſions, they aſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed new Courage, levied more Men, and crowned their King with the utmoſt Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, as the Indigency and Neceſſity of their Affairs would admit. The <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> on the other Side, being reſolved to terminate this War with <hi>Scotland,</hi> paſſed over into <hi>Fife,</hi> and having defeated four thouſand <hi>Scots,</hi> they ſoon became Maſters of <hi>Inchigravy, Burntiſland,</hi> and <hi>St. John<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoun:</hi> Mean while the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of 16000 abandoned their own Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, and, by the Way of <hi>Carliſle,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <hi>England.</hi> General <hi>Cromwel</hi> advertiſed hereof, leaves Colonel <hi>Monk</hi> with 7000 Men in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to perfect the Conqueſt of that Kingdom, and with the reſt of the Army purſues the <hi>Scots;</hi> who, whereſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they came, proclaimed their King, to be King of <hi>Great Britain, France,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> &amp;c. But few ſtirred unto their Aid, among others, the unfortunate Earl of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:54496:10"/>
               <hi>Darby,</hi> who having aſſembled 1200 Men, in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> was defeated by Colonel <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn,</hi> and to ſave himſelf was conſtrained to flee to <hi>Worceſter;</hi> where the <hi>Scots,</hi> after a long and tedious March, had pitch'd their Camp, whither General <hi>Cromwel</hi> ſoon purſued; and having the Aid of the Train Bands of ſeveral Counties, gave them Battle, which proved fatal unto the <hi>Scots,</hi> their whole Army being overthrown. The King in a Diſguiſe eſcaped into <hi>France,</hi> not without much Difficulty and Danger, the Parliament having promiſed five hundred Pounds to any one that could diſcover his Perſon. Such a Liſt of Priſoners as were then taken, we ſhall ſeldom meet with in any Battle but <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s, the Earl of <hi>Dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> Duke <hi>Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> General of the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards died of his Wounds, the Earl of <hi>Rothes,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Cornwarth,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury, Peckington, Cunninghame,</hi> and <hi>Clare,</hi> Knights; the Lord <hi>Spine,</hi> and <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Cleveland,</hi> of <hi>Kelley,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Greaves,</hi> ſix Colonels of Horſe, thirteen of Foot, nine Lieutenant Colonels of Horſe, eight of Foot, ſix Majors of Horſe, thirteen of Foot, ſeven and thirty Captains of Horſe, ſeventy three of Foot, fifth five Quarter-maſters, eighty nine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54496:11"/>Lieutenants of Foot, Major General <hi>Biſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Major General <hi>Montgomery,</hi> the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant General of the Ordnance, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutant General of the Foot, the Marſhal General, the Quartermaſter General, the Conductor General of the Baggage, ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſix Standards, ninety nine Enſigns; all which were hung up in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> for ſucceſſive Parliaments, to underſtand what Vigour of Spirits, they, by their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence, can infuſe into thoſe they pleaſe pleaſe to authorize, only the Want of the Allay of their Ambitions, often works them high, where it is impoſſible to ſet limits to generous Minds. To continue the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Appendixes to this Victory, there were alſo taken nine Miniſters, nine Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons, One hundred fifty and eight Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and all the Cannon and Baggage ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, the Royal Standard, the King's Coach and Horſes, the Royal Robe, the Collar of the Order of the Garter, thirty of his domeſtick Servants, and that admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Poet, his Secretary, <hi>Fanſhaw.</hi> Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Perſons were alſo afterwards ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the remoteſt Countries, as Major General <hi>Maſſey</hi> (who being committed to the Tower, afterwards made his Eſcape) Major General <hi>Middleton,</hi> Lieutenant Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>David Leſly,</hi> inſomuch as that it may
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54496:11"/>be ſaid, the Gleanings of this Victory, were as conſiderable as the whole Harveſt itſelf. Many of the common Soldiers were tranſported into <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> and other Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations; this Mercy extended to them in ſaving their Lives, cauſing much Gain to accrue thereby unto the Commonwealth, in ſelling the poor heatheniſh Highlanders to the Plantations. I ſhall end theſe ſad Tranſactions with what Mr. <hi>Wharton</hi> chron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologized in theſe Words, <hi>Since</hi> England<hi>'s Hogs eat our dear Brethren up.</hi> He only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects on the half Graves were made for them in <hi>Tuttle</hi> Fields.</p>
            <p>Of all this long Liſt two only ſuffer'd Death, <hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Timothy Featherſtone</hi> Knight, and the Earl of <hi>Darby,</hi> who, on the 15th of <hi>October</hi> following, was beheaded at <hi>Bol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> in <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> being conducted thither by ſixty Foot, and eighty Horſe, about two of the Clock he was brought forth to the Scaffold, which was built at the Croſs, part of it with the Timber of his own Houſe at <hi>Latham,</hi> there was not above an hundred Lookers on, beſides Soldiers; preſently after his coming upon the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold there happen'd a great Tumult. (the Occaſion whereof was not certainly known) in appeaſing of which there were ſome cut, many hurt, and one Child killed. The
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54496:12"/>Earl was no eloquent Orator, and the Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult put him out of his ſpeaking what he intended: At laſt, after ſome Silence made, he began as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Since it hath pleaſed God, by this untimely Death to ſhorten my Days, I am glad it is in this Town, where ſome have been made believe I was a cruel Perſon, that I might vindicate myſelf from this Aſperſion: It was my Deſire, the laſt Time I came into this Country, to come hither, as to a People that ought to ſerve the King, as I conceive, upon good Grounds: It was ſaid, that I was accuſtomed to be a Man of Blood; but it doth not lie upon my Conſcience, I was wrongfully bely'd. I thank God I deſir'd Peace. I was born in Honour, and I ſhall die Honourably, as I ſuffer for my Sovereign. I had a fair Eſtate, good Friends, and was reſpected, and do reſpect: Thoſe that were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to do for me, I was ready to do for them. I have done nothing, but as my generous Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors acted, to do you good. It was the King that called me in, and I thought it my Duty to wait upon his Highneſs, to do him Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here he was diſturb'd by the Noiſe of the People, after ſome Pauſe he ſaid, <hi>I intended to have expreſt my ſelf further, but I have ſaid. I have not much more to ſay to you, but as to my Good-will to this Town of</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:54496:12"/>Bolton, <hi>I can ſay no more, but the Lord bleſs you. I forgive you all, and deſire to be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of you all, for I put my Truſt in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus.</hi> Looking about him he ſaid, <hi>I did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deſerve this hard Meaſure. Honeſt Friends, (you that are Soldiers) my Life is taken away, after Quarter given, by a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of War, which was never done before.</hi> Walking up and down the Scaffold he ſaid, <hi>The Lord bleſs you all, the Son of God bleſs you all of this Town of</hi> Bolton, Manchaſter, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſhire, <hi>and the reſt of the Kingdom; and God ſend that you may have a King again, and Laws. I die like a Chriſtian, and a Soldier, God and my Sovereign's Soldier.</hi> Cauſing his Coffin to be opened, he ſaid, <hi>I hope when I'm impriſon'd here, armed Men ſhall not need to watch me.</hi> Looking upon them that were upon the Scaffold, he ſaid, <hi>What do you ſtay for? it is hard that I cannot get a Block to have my Head cut off.</hi> Speaking to the Executioner, he ſaid, <hi>Thy Coat is ſo troubleſome and cumberſome, that I believe that thou canſt not het right, the Lord help thee and ſorgive thee.</hi> Other Words he uſed, which to avoid Proxillty I willingly omit. At laſt ſubmitting his Neck to the Block, he had his Head ſevered from his Body with one Blow; his ſorrowful Son, who was a ſad Spectator of this woful Tragedy, out
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54496:13"/>of a pious care, and filial duty, conveyed his Corps back with him that Night to <hi>Wiggan,</hi> and afterwards gave them honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Burial.</p>
            <p>Not long before at <hi>London</hi> was Colonel <hi>Euſebius Andrews</hi> apprehended, who having formerly practiced the Law, changed his Gown into a Coat of Armour, having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a Commiſſion from the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> for the raiſing Men in <hi>England,</hi> he was tryed in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> at the High Court of Juſtice, then again newly erected, being the firſt unfortunate Centleman that hanſelled the Court. He was condemned, and the 22. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1650. brought to the Scaffold on <hi>Tower-hill,</hi> where he expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelf to the People in theſe his laſt Words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian Gentlemen and People, your Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hither to Day is to ſee a ſad Spectacle, a Man to be in a Moment unman'd, and cut off in the prime of his Years, taken from further opportunities of doing good either to himſelf, his Friends, the Common-wealth, or more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as to my continued ſervices to my Creator. Truly, if my general known Courſe of Life were but enquired into, I may modeſtly ſay, there is ſuch a moral Honeſty upon it, as ſome may be ſo ſawcy as to expoſtulate why this great Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is fallen upon me; but know I am able
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:54496:13"/>to give them and my ſelf an anſwer, and out of this Breaſt am able to give a better Accompt of my Judgement and Execution then my Judgers themſelves, or you are able to give: It is Gods wrath upon me for Sins long unrepented of, many Judgements withſtood, and Mercies ſlighted; therefore God hath whipped me by his ſevere Rod of Correction, that he might not loſe me. I pray join with me in Prayer, that it may not be a fruitleſs Rod, that when by this Rod I have laid down my Life, by his Staff I may be comforted, and received into Glory. I am very conſident by what I have heard ſince my Sentence there is more exceptions made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt proceedings againſt me, then I ever made. My Triers had a Law, and the value of that Law is undiſputable; and for me to make a queſtion of it, I ſhould ſhame my ſelf and my Diſcretion. In the ſtrictneſs of that Law, ſomething is done by me, that is applicable to ſome clauſe therein, by which I ſtand condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. The means whereby I was brought under that Interpretation of that which was not in my ſelf intended maliciouſly, there being Teſtimony given, (by Perſons whom I pity) ſo falſe, yet ſo poſitive, that I cannot condemn my Judges, for paſſing ſentence againſt me, according to Legal Juſtice, though Equity lieth in the higher Breaſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:54496:14"/>
               <hi>As for my Accuſers. or rather Betrayers, I pity, and am ſorry for them; they have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> Judas<hi>'s Crime, but I wiſh and pray for them with</hi> Peter's <hi>Tears, that by</hi> Peter's <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance they may eſcape</hi> Judas<hi>'s Puniſhment; and I wiſh other People ſo happy, they may be taken up betimes, before they have drunk more Blood of Chriſtian Men, poſſibly leſs deſerving then my ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is true, there have been ſeveral Addreſſes made for Mercy, and I will put the Obſtruction of it upon nothing more than my own Sin; and ſeeing God ſees it fit, (having not glorified him in my Life) I might do it in my Death, which I am contented to do; I profeſs in the fear of God, particular Malice to any one of State or Parliament, to do them a bodily Injury I had none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the cauſe in which I had long waded, I muſt needs ſay, my engagement or continuance in it hath laid no ſcruple upon my Conſcience; it was on Principles of Law, the Knowledge whereof I profeſs, and on Principles of Religion, my Judgement ſatisfied, and Conſcience rectifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that I have purſued thoſe ways which I bleſs God I find no blackneſs upon my Conſcience, nor have I put it into the Bed-roll of my Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will not preſume to decide controverſies; I deſire God to honour himſelf in proſpering that ſide that hath right with it, and that you may
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54496:14"/>enjoy Peace and Plenty, beyond all you poſſeſs here. In my Converſation in the World, I do not know where I have an Enemy with cauſe, or that there is ſuch a Perſon whom I have to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret; but if there be any whom I cannot recol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, under the notion of chriſtian Men, I pardon them as freely as if I had named them by name, I freely forgive them, being in free Peace with all the World, as I deſire God for Chriſts ſake, to be at Peace with me. For the buſineſs of Death it is a ſad Sentence in it ſelf, if Men conſult with Fleſh and Blood: But truly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out boaſting, I ſay it, or if I do boaſt, I boaſt in the Lord, I have not to this minute had one conſultation with the Fleſh about the blow of the Axe, more then as my paſsport to Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I take it for an honour, and I owe thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to thoſe under whoſe Power I am, that they ſent me hither to a place, however of Puniſhment, yet of ſome Honour, to die a death ſomewhat worthy of my Blood, anſwerable to my Birth and Qualification, and this courteſie of theirs much helped towards the pacification of my Mind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I ſhall deſire God that thoſe Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lemen in that ſad Bed-roll to be tryed by the High Court of Juſtice, that they may find that really there, that is nominal in the Act, an High Court of Juſtice, a Court of High Juſtice, high in its Righteouſneſs, though not in its ſeverity. Father forgive them, and forgive me as I forgive them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:54496:15"/>
               <hi>I deſire you now that you would pray for me, and not give over praying till the Hour of my Death, not till the Moment of my Death, for the Hour is come already, the inſtant of Time approaches, that as I have a great load of Sins, ſo I may have the wings of your Prayers, to help thoſe Angels that are to convey my Soul to Heaven; and I doubt not but I ſhall ſee my</hi> Saviour, <hi>and my gallant Maſter</hi> the King of England, <hi>and another Maſter whom I much honoured,</hi> my Lord <hi>Capel, hoping this Day to ſee my</hi> Chriſt <hi>in the preſence of the</hi> Father, <hi>the</hi> King <hi>in the preſence of him, my Lord</hi> Capel <hi>in the preſence of them all; and my</hi> ſelf <hi>there to rejoyce with all other Saints and Angels for ever more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the uttering of theſe and many the like Words, declaring his Faith and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God, with as much undaunted, yet Chriſtian Courage, as poſſibly could be in Man, he expoſed his Neck to the fatal Ax, commending his Soul into the Hands of a faithful and merciful Creator, thro' the meritorious Paſſion of a gracious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; and having ſaid <hi>Lord Jeſus receive me</hi> the Executioner with one Blow ſevered his Head from his Body.</p>
            <p>For ſuch a collateral deſign, not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one Maſter <hi>Benſon</hi> was executed at <hi>Tyburn,</hi> one that had ſome Relations to Sir
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54496:15"/>
               <hi>John Gell,</hi> who was tried for the ſame Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiraccy, with his Man: Sir <hi>John</hi>'s former Services to the Parliament, being his beſt and moſt aſſured Interceſſors for his Life, and at that time were more then ordinary Advantages to him.</p>
            <p>I ſhall in the next place give you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Beheading of Sir <hi>Henry Hide.</hi> He was by the <hi>Scots</hi> King commiſſonated as Ambaſſadour to the Grand <hi>Signior</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and ſtood in Competition with Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh</hi> (then Ambaſſadour for the Engliſh) for his Place; whereupon they had a Hearing before the <hi>Vizier Baſſa;</hi> the reſult whereof was, that Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh</hi> ſhould diſpoſe of the ſaid Sir <hi>Henry Hide,</hi> as he thought good; who was to the ſame purpoſe ſent to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> thence into <hi>England,</hi> and there condemned and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted before the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>London, March</hi> 4. 1650.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <head>His laſt Words were to this Effect.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CHriſtian People,</hi> I come hither to die, I am brought hither to die; and that I may die Chriſtian like, I humbly beſeech the aſſiſtance of your Chriſtian Prayers, that by the benefit of them my paſſage may be the more eaſie: Yet becauſe Men in that condition, which it hath pleaſed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54496:16"/>God to reduce me to, give the more credit to Speech; in the diſcharge of my Duty towards God, I ſhall uſe a few Words and ſo conclude.</p>
                  <p>I pray all of you join with me to praiſe this Almighty God, to whom I deſire to render all hearty Thanks; as for all his Mercies, ſo in particular for this, that he hath brought me hither; that whereas I owe a Debt to Sin and and to Nature, that now I can pay the Debt to Nature, I can pay it upon the account of Grace. And becauſe it is fit to render the bleſſed account of that hope that is in me, I ſhall tell you, to the praiſe of Almighty God, that I have been born and bred up in the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I have no negative Religion, believing to be ſaved by the only merits of my Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and whatſoever elſe is profeſt in the Doctrine and Diſcipline of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> authorized by Law; humbly beſeeching Almighay God to reſtore unto this Church her Peace, Proſperity and Patrimony, whereof I have an Obedient and a Loving (however an unworthy) Son; and now both my Hope being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and my Faith perfected, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains only Chriſtian Charity; Charity we carry into Heaven, Charity on Earth;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54496:16"/>that I leave, beſeeching all whomſoever I have offended to forgive me, as I from the bottom of my Heart do all whomſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever; bleſſing Almighty God for the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py advantage he takes to bring me the ſooner to Heaven; I bleſs Almighty God that he hath given me this Advantage, as he hath been Merciful to me before the Foundation of the World, in my Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, ſo that now he hath in Mercy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured me, with a ſuffering for his Name, in Obedience to his Commandment.</p>
                  <p>On this Day ſevennight I was ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before that Juſtice, which condemned me on <hi>Friday</hi> laſt, praiſed be Almighty God, that by this way he hath brought me nearer to himſelf. My charge I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume is publick, as my Puniſhment is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; if there have been any thing in the management of my part, being unskilful, having diſcontinued my own Countrey many Years, I ſhall beſeech the Chriſtian Charity of all you my beloved Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to impute it rightly to the Ignorance of my unskilful ways of managing of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; it was objected unto me there, that I had a vanity of delighting in ſtrange Tongues; I do acknowledge that I was beſt skilled in the <hi>Italian,</hi> (but free from that vanity, I thank Almighty God) and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:54496:17"/>therefore I would in defence of my Life, (if it had been the cuſtom here, or the Judges favour) have uſed that Language, which was almoſt as natural to me as my Mother Tongue.</p>
                  <p>It was objected, that I did not ſo freely as a thorow-paced Cavalier, own my Maſter: I was told ſince I came into <hi>England</hi> (this Skill I have in our Laws) that a legal denyal in Law might be tolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; I hope I did not exceed the bounds of that in any thing, for God forbid that I ſhould be aſhamed of ſerving ſo pious a Maſter; <hi>(putting off his Hat)</hi> for this I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice, and I humbly beſeech Almighty God to fill my Heart and my Tongue, and all that hear me this Day, with thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for it.</p>
                  <p>As to the Buſineſs, that another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction had been made and believ'd here, then what was there, the righteous God knoweth it; if any weakneſs were in the management, that was mine. I was ſent to ſerve and protect, not to injure any, as God acquits me of the Intention of matter of Fact, as having not done any manner of Evil that way, however here underſtood, bleſſed be his holy Name (again putting off his Hat) ſo thoſe Gentlemen of the Turky Company, if they would might
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54496:17"/>acknowledge, for they know it very well, the impoſſibility of my doing them any manner of harm. Whereas that of the Embaſſy objected againſt me, that my Maſter honoured me with it, though I was never worthy of it; I was his Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger and <hi>Internuntio</hi> for the conſervation only of his good Subjects, of all the Merchants, until ſuch time as he could confirm that Gentlemen now Reſident, or to ſend any other; and they themſelves know that there was an unpoſſibility (as I bleſs God there was an innocency in me) unto any ſuch Intention to do them harm; for my Maſters commands were point blank the contrary: I was only ſent for their good; as I never owned the Title ſo the very Letters them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſpeaking no other: I never did ſo much as think of any manner of addreſs to the grand Signior, but gave him the Letter from my Maſter; the reſt of the Engliſh Nation that were there preſent, may, when they pleaſe, aſſert ſo much. This I would inſert, that thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as they have been Loſers by the miſcarriages of others, may now have a breach of their Charity with me; but if it be, as it ſeems it is now in this Country, a Sin to be Loyal, I hope my God hath
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54496:18"/>forgiven that, when it is upon harmlefs Employment, not invading any, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to my juſt Maſters order; for indeed I have been always bred up in the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Loyalty, my Allegiance hath been incorporated into my Religion, and I have thought it a great part of the ſervice due from me to Almighty God, to ſerve the King (again putting off his Hat.) He ſaid, I need not make any Apology for any thing in relation to the preſent Affairs in <hi>England,</hi> for were I (as I ſpake before my Judges) were I as evil as my Sentence here hath made black, it were impoſſible for me to have prejudiced any body in <hi>England,</hi> or to <hi>England</hi> belonging, in that Employment; But I bleſs God for his infinite Mercy in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath taken me to himſelf by this manner of way, it was the beſt Phyſick for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of my Soul, and thoſe that have done it, have no more Power than that of my Body; I leave nothing behind me, but that I am willing to part withal; all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> am going to, is deſirable; and that you may all know that Almighty God hath wrought in me a total denyal of my ſelf and that there is that perfect reformation of me within, of my own Corruptions, by the bleſſed Aſſiſtance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hs Holy Spirit
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:54496:18"/>I deſire Almighty God in the Abundance of the Bowels of his Mercy in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> not only to forgive every Enemy, (if any ſuch be in the World, here or whereſoever) but to bring him into his Boſom, ſo much good and particular Comfort, as he may at any time, whether the Cauſe were juſt or unjuſt, have wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me any manner of Evil; for I take him to be the happy Inſtrument of bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me to Heaven. I am tedious, but I have an inward comfort, I bleſs Almighty God: (pray Gentlemen give leave, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſome that preſt upon him) I ſhould never do it but to give ſatisfaction to all charitable Hearts. I have been trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Here he made a Pauſe, as diſcontented at the diſturbance of thoſe on the Scaffold, when the Sheriff ſaid to him, <hi>Sir, you have your Liberty to ſpeak more if you pleaſe,</hi> at length he proceeded.</p>
            <q>
               <p>But as to that part, Mr. Sheriff, that did concern the denyal (as it was aſſirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Maſter Attorney General) of my Maſters Employment; truly, landing at <hi>White Hall,</hi> I told that Council, there was warrantable Commiſſions to an old Officer, which by the Bleſſing of God, I have by me, and I have other acceptable
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54496:19"/>things that God hath bleſſed me withal; we that are Merchants abroad, we allow our ſelves any ſufferance that may induce to our own ſafety, Inlargement of Trade, or Preſervation of what is ours. Why I had by the favour of my gracious Maſter, a confirmation of my old Comiſſion of <hi>Conſulage</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> but as to the Embaſſy, no more then my credential Letters did ſpeak, nor no more then that I attempted, an <hi>Internucio</hi> they call it in thoſe places, which is a Meſſenger between the one and the other King, they both unhappily dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of ſeveral Deaths, and both violent too; and it is a cuſtom not unknown to you, Maſter Sheriff, and other Gentlemen that practiſe in the World, that Princes of courſe, for the continuation of Amity do ſend Meſſengers where there is Pence, that the tranſaction of thoſe publick ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of reciprocal affections may be performed; but for Embaſſy, God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid I ſhould own it, I never had it, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they have uſed it as the happy means to bring me to God this Day, whom I in the Bowels of my Saviour beſeech to forgive thoſe People that have done it; I owe them no harm, God return better things into their Boſoms with all the good of this; and an everlaſting Life.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:54496:19"/>
As for my part, I have been long ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I have meddled with no Affairs in <hi>England;</hi> ſufficient to me is God's grace to the Salvation of my Soul.</p>
               <p>I have been always fearful of offending God, according to the Grace he hath given me; but to learn a new Religion, or new ways, (that I muſt ſay Mr. Sheriff to you, and all others that hear me) I could never diſpence with my Conſcience to give offence to Almighty God. I am now (if it may be with your Commiſſion Maſter Sheriff) to pour out my Soul to Almighty God in two or three Words (the place is ſtraitned) if I knew wherein to give any ſatisfaction to any Perſon whatſoever that imagines I have offended him, or he me, I am here in the fear of God to do it. I forgive them with all my Soul, and my forgiveneſs is clear, as I am now going to receive Happineſs at the Hand of my Saviour; if I thought it were ſatisfaction to Sir <hi>Thomas Bendiſh,</hi> and all the Company, or any who think they have offended me, I am come, Maſter Sheriff, to pay that Debt I owe to nature, to pay it upon the Score of a Loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; my Conſcience within me inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me, that for the intentions of ſerving my Prince, I could not deſerve ſuch a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54496:20"/>Death, though ten thouſand times more other ways.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Having expreſſed himſelf to this effect with much meekneſs, he ſubmitted his Neck to the Ax, having firſt ſaid, <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my Soul,</hi> the Executioner at one blow ſevered his Head from his Body.</p>
            <p>Not long after <hi>Brown Buſhel</hi> was behead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under the Scaffold on <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> one who had formerly done great ſervice to the Royal Party both by Sea and Land; crimes of ſuch a Nature, as brought him into compaſs of Piracy, and then of high Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>Soon after enſuing the Deaths of Mr. <hi>Love</hi> and Mr. <hi>Gibbons,</hi> who were beheaded ed on <hi>Tower-hill</hi> the 22. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1651. Their Crimes objected, were, for combin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Scots to re-eſtabliſh <hi>Charles Stuart.</hi> many others were apprehended upon the ſame Account, but theſe two on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffered.</p>
            <p>Paſſing over theſe Golgotha's, the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der may be pleas'd to underſtand, that all theſe Perſons here mentioned, (ſave only the Earl of <hi>Darby</hi>) ſuffered Death before that memorable Battle at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> though in our Hiſtory we have related them after, as not willing to diſcontinue the ſeries of our affairs with <hi>Scotland</hi> by ſuch diverſions.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54496:20"/>But to return to matters of more publick concernment, the Iſles of <hi>Jerſey, Jernſey</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> who had hitherto held for the King, ſubmitted themſelves; ſo that now all ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed quiet, when ſuddenly a War brake forth with <hi>Holland,</hi> began only at firſt upon points of Honour at Sea, <hi>Van Trump</hi> the Dutch Admiral refuſing to vail his Flag, a Ceremonial Honour which the Engliſh ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate to themſelves, as being Lords of theſe narrow Seas, whereupon a ſharp Fight enſued betwixt them, wherein the Dutch were diſcomfited, one of their Ships ſunk, and another of thirty Guns taken, with the Captains of both, and about a hundred and fifty Priſoners.</p>
            <p>This Skirmiſh produced open War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two Nations, notwithſtanding Overtures of Peace made by the Hollander. General <hi>Blake,</hi> the Engliſh Admiral, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes twelve Dutch Men of War towards the Iſles of <hi>Orkney,</hi> Sir <hi>George Aſcue</hi> in the Road betwixt <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Calice,</hi> ſets upon their Fleet, being thirty in Number, of which ten were taken and burnt, the reſt hardly eſcaping. Soon after near <hi>Pliniouth</hi> he gave them another Fight, wherein the Dutch went again by the worſt. Theſe ſucceſſes were ſeconded by others very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, General <hi>Blake</hi> ſteering North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54496:21"/>took ſix Holland Ships of a great Value about the <hi>Downes.</hi> Captain <hi>Penne</hi> alſo took ſix more upon the Coaſt of <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after, the Navies engaged in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Fight at a place called the <hi>Kentiſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ock,</hi> wherein the Dutch were again de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, eleven of their Men of War ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on four of the Engliſh in the <hi>Straights,</hi> took the Phenix Frigot, and much damaged the other. In a ſhort ſpace after, another Sea Engagement enſued on the Back-ſide of <hi>Goodwin Sands,</hi> wherein the Engliſh were worſted, four Ships taken, and a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Loſs of Men. The greateſt Fight of all was near the <hi>Iſle of Wight</hi> and <hi>Portland,</hi> wherein the Dutch received a great Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, fifty Merchants being taken, nine Men of War, above two thouſand ſlain, and fifteen hundred taken Priſoners. But this great Victory ſoon after received a check, the Engliſh Fleet in the Levant Seas being again worſted by the Dutch, with the Loſs of divers Ships and Men.</p>
            <p>But leaving off theſe Affairs for a time, let us come to General <hi>Cromwel;</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for the better accompliſhing of his own Deſigns, the dialtory proceedings, pernicious and arbitrary actings in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to perpetuate their Seſſion, to be very dangerous, and enthrall the Nation;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54496:21"/>this train of his he knew would take well with the People; he therefore reſolved to put a Period to the Parliament, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly accompanied by the chief Officers of the Army, he entered the Houſe, and having declared his Intentions, ſome by force, ſome through fear, and others not without a great deal of reluctancy and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, departed the Houſe. To ſet a fair gloſs upon what he had done, and to give ſome ſatisfaction to the People, he publiſhes a Declaration, the ſubſtance whereof fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>That after God was pleaſed marvelous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to appear for his People, in reducing <hi>Ireland</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> to ſo great a Peace, and <hi>England</hi> to perfect quiet; whereby the Parliament had opportunity to give the People the Harveſt of all their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, Blood, and Treaſure; and to ſettle a due Liberty in reference to Civil and Spiritual things; whereunto they were obliged by their Duty, Engagements, and thoſe great and wonderful things God hath wrought for them. But they made ſo little Progreſs therein, that it was mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of much Grief to the good People of the Land; who thereupon applied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Army, expecting redreſs by their means, who (though unwilling to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54496:22"/>meddle with the Civil Authority) agreed that ſuch Officers as were Members of Parliament ſhould move them to proceed vigorouſly, in reforming what was amiſs in the Common-wealth, and in ſettling it upon a foundation of Juſtice and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; which being done, it was hoped the Parliament would have anſwered their expectations.</p>
               <p>But finding the contrary, they renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their deſires by an humble Petition in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1652, which produced no conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable effects, nor was any ſuch Progreſs made therein, as might imply their real Intentions to accompliſh what was peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned for; but rather an averſeneſs to the things themſelves, with much bitterneſs and oppoſition to the People of God, and his Spirit acting in them; inſomuch, that the Godly Party in Parliament were ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of no further uſe, then to counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance the ends of a corrupt party, for ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting their deſires of perpetuating them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the ſupream Government.</p>
               <p>For obviating theſe evils, the Officers of the Army obtained ſeveral meetings with ſome of the Parliament, to conſider what remedy might be applied to prevent the ſame; but ſuch endeavours proving ineffectual, it became evident, that this
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54496:22"/>Parliament, through the corruption of ſome, the jealouſie of others non-atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of many; would never anſwer thoſe ends which God, his People, and the whole Nation expected from them: But that this cauſe which God had ſo greatly bleſſed, muſt needs languiſh under their Hands, and by degrees be loſt; and the Lives, Liberties, and Comforts of his People be delivered into their Enemies Hands.</p>
               <p>All which being ſadly and ſeriouſly conſidered by the honeſt People of the Nation, as well as by the Army, it ſeemed a Duty incumbent upon us, who had ſeen much of the power and preſence of God, to conſider of ſome effectual means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to eſtabliſh Righteouſneſs and Peace in theſe Nations.</p>
               <p>And after much debate it was judged neceſſary, that the Supream Government ſhould be by the Parliament devolved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on known Perſons fearing God, and of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved integrity for a time, as the moſt hopeful way to countenance all God's People, reform the Law, and adminiſter Juſtice impartially; hoping thereby the People might forget Monarchy, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their true Intereſt in the election of ſucceſſive Parliaments; that ſo the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54496:23"/>might be ſettled upon a right Baſis, without hazard to this glorious cauſe, or neceſſitating to keep up Armies for the defence of the ſame.</p>
               <p>And being ſtill reſolved to uſe all means poſſibly to avoid extraordiany courſes, we prevailed with about twenty Members of Parliament, to give us a conference, with whom we plainly debated the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity and juſtneſs of our Propoſals: The which found no acceptance, but inſtead thereof it was offered, that the way was to continue ſtill this Parliament, as being that from which we might probably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect all good things. This being vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently inſiſted on, did much confirm us in our apprehenſions: That not any love to a Repreſentative, but the making uſe thereof to recruit, and ſo to perpetuate themſelves, was their aim, in the Act they had then under conſideration.</p>
               <p>For preventing the conſumating where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and all the ſad and evil conſequences, which upon the grounds a foreſaid muſt have enſued, and whereby at one Blow the intereſt of all honeſt Men and of this glorious Cauſe had been endangered to be laid in the duſt, and theſe Nations em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyled in new Troubles, at a time when our Enemies abroad are watching all Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54496:23"/>againſt, and ſome of them actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally engaged in War with us, we have been neceſſitated (though with much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy) to put an end to this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </q>
            <p>This Declaration was ſeconded by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſettling a Councel of State, to give ſome Satisfaction to the People what Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they intended; which Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the Readers further Satisfaction, take as followeth.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="declaration">
               <body>
                  <p>Whereas the Parliament being diſſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Perſons of approved Fidelity and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty are (according to the late Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the 22. of <hi>April</hi> laſt) to be called from the ſeveral parts of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth to the Supream Authority; and although effectual proceedings are and have been had for perfecting thoſe Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, yet ſome convenient time being required for the aſſembling of thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, it hath been found neceſſary for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the miſchiefs and inconveniencies which may ariſe in the mean while to the publick Affairs, that a Councel of State be conſtituted, to take care of and intend the Peace, Safety, and preſent Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Affairs of this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; which being ſettled accordingly, the ſame is hereby declared and publiſhed,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54496:24"/>to the end all Perſons may take notice thereof, and in their ſeveral places and Stations, demean themſelves peaceably, giving Obedience to the Laws of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as heretofore; in the exerciſe and adminiſtration thereof, as endeavours ſhall be uſed, that no oppreſſion or wrong ſhall be done to the People, ſo a ſtrict accompt will be required of all ſuch as ſhall do any thing to endanger the Publick peace and quiet upon any pretence whatſoever. <hi>April</hi> 30. 1653.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>O. Cromwel.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Theſe domeſtick revolutions put new Life into the Dutch, who hoping from theſe Diſtractions to reap a Victory over the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, with great confidence put forth again to Sea; thinking upon nothing ſo much as Chapmen for the Engliſh Fleet, ſaying; <hi>It was to be cried out by the ſound of Trumpet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and Horns.</hi> But they were deceived in their expectation; for coming to a Fight, on the North Foreland, near unto the South poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>Gobes,</hi> their Fleet was defeated eleven Men of War, and two Water Hove being taken, beſides ſix Captains and fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred Priſoners, and ſix Men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> War which were ſunk.</p>
            <p>Not long after, to ſet the better face o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his reſolute proceedings, <hi>Cromwel</hi> calls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:54496:24"/>another Parliament convened at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> who met <hi>July</hi> 4. 1653. to whom Generall <hi>Cromwel</hi> made a long Speech. Then he produced an Inſtrument under his own Hand and Seal, whereby the Supream Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Nation was devolved upon them, unto whom all Perſons were to yeild obedience and ſubjection. He delared that they were to ſit no longer then the third of <hi>November</hi> 1654. and three months be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their diſſolution they were to make choice of others to ſucceed them, who were not to ſit above twelve months, and then to take care for a ſucceſſion in Government.</p>
            <p>Now was the time come for the train to take the Dutch, having, as hath been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, caſt the Urine of the preſent Affairs, being quite tired with then continual loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſent Commiſſioners over into <hi>England</hi> to treat of Peace. It hath been the reſult of the opinions of thoſe that had their Eyes in their Heads, that the Dutch thought to have made up their Mouths, to have taken our Navy napping in the time of the Treaty the Fight happening betwixt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and us; but they found it otherwiſe, their whole Fleet was put to ſlight, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Van Trump,</hi> a Man of eminent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> being ſlain, about thirty Men of War ſuck and fired, ſix Captains, and about a thouſand
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54496:25"/>Men taken Priſoners, and about ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſlain. This great Victory did not a little conduce to haſten the concluſion of the Peace, but on ſuch terms as were at that time more honourable for his preſent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, than advantageous to the Engliſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For this ſervice, gold Chains were preſented to the Generals, <hi>Blake, Monk, Renne,</hi> and <hi>Lawſon,</hi> and to the other Flag Captains; and ſilver Medals to the other Officers of the Fleet.</p>
            <p>The Parliament having ſat about as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Weeks as the other had done Years, they diſſolved themſelves, immediately making way for General <hi>Cromwel,</hi> by their diſſolution, to be choſen Lord Protector of the Common-wealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of all the Iſlands and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories thereunto belonging, <hi>December,</hi> the 16, 1653. The Articles of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to which he ſigned are as followeth.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That his Excellency be chief Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the three Nations of <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That he will, call to his aſſiſtance Councellors, not under the Number of thirteen, nor above twenty one.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That he ſhall not act without the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Council.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:54496:25"/>
4. That here ſhall be every three Years a Parliament called, freely choſen, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in <hi>September</hi> next, <hi>viz.</hi> four hundred, and the Number for every County pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That no Parliament ſhall adjourn till they have ſat above five Months.</p>
            <p n="6">6. When ever any Bill is paſſed in Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, the Lord Protector ſhall have twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Days to adviſe with his Council; if he ſign it not in twenty Days, it ſhall paſs without, unleſs contrary to theſe Articles.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That no Parliament be diſſolved by the Protector, but end every three Years, and the Protector to iſſue out Warrants.</p>
            <p n="8">8. All the Crown Revenues left, to go to the maintenance of the Lord Protector.</p>
            <p n="9">9. To make Peace or War as he pleaſeth, with the advice of his Council, in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terval of Parliaments; but not to raiſe Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney without the Parliament, unleſs in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Cauſes.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Whatſoever goes out in the name of the <hi>Keepers of the Liberties of</hi> England, to go out in the Name of the <hi>Lord Protector.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. That it is Treaſon to ſpeak againſt the preſent Government.</p>
            <p n="12">12. That all forfeited and confiſcated Eſtates go to the maintenance of the Lord Protector.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:54496:26"/>
13. That all Acts of Parliaments made, and Eſtates ſold, ſtand good and be enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p n="14">14. That the Lord Protector have Power to confer titles of Honour, and to diſpoſe of the great Places of truſt.</p>
            <p n="15">15. That in the interval of Parliaments, the Lord Protector, with his Council<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do order the Affairs of the Nation.</p>
            <p n="16">16. That all Articles of War be kept.</p>
            <p n="17">17. That the known Laws of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth be continued.</p>
            <p n="18">18. That a ſtanding Army be maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of ten thouſand Horſe, and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Foot.</p>
            <p n="19">19. That Chriſtian Religion be maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſuch as is contained in the Word of God.</p>
            <p n="20">20. That all Perſons ſhall have Liberty of Conſcience, provided that they diſturb not the Civil Government, except the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh and Prelatical party.</p>
            <p n="21">21. That no Papiſt, or Delinquent in Arms ſince the Year 1649, elect, or be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, a Parliament Man, under Penalty of forfeiture of one Years revenue, and the Moiety of his perſonal Eſtate.</p>
            <p n="22">22. That the Lord Protector have Power to pardon all Offenders, except Murther.</p>
            <p n="23">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:54496:26"/>
23. That Writs be iſſued out in <hi>Jul</hi> next for ſummoning the Parliament, either by the Protector, or in courſe.</p>
            <p n="24">24. That when the Protector dies, the Council then ſitting ſhall ſummon all the Members of the Council, the Major part to elect one to be Protector before they ſtir out of the Council Chamber, and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo choſen, not to be under the age of twenty one Years, nor of the Family of the <hi>Stuarts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Articles ſworn to, he was proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lord Protector in the <hi>Palace-yard,</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and by the Lord Mayor and Aldermen in their Scarlet Gowns at the <hi>Royal Exchange;</hi> who to ingratiate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with their new Governour, beſtowed on him a coſtly Feaſt at <hi>Grocers Hall;</hi> it is an uſual obſervation that Perſons that make their ways with their Swords, that their ſhows to take the People, generaly are more ſtately then thoſe of ſucceſſive Princes; what he admitted of, as with his own permiſſion, was nothing to thoſe duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſolemnities that purſued his Memory; without diſpute he had ſtudied the art and ordinance of ſelf-denying, inſomuch that the Parliament perceiving that he did but complement his Generalſhip, which he might with ſafety and moſt right have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54496:27"/>they preſſed him the leſs, as he ſeemed to puſh away that with his little finger that they were certain he was ready to graſp with both his Hands.</p>
            <p>The greateſt Admiration that hath fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized me, hath been what in the compaſs of a Year I have obſerved, the Tides and Streams of Petitions out of moſt Counties, that at the firſt riſe or promiſe of greatneſs have purſued every alteration, as Party-coloured as <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Coat, and as variable as the Rainbow; it is not to depictured how <hi>Janus</hi>-faced they have been on all occaſions, with how many religious expreſſions and wiſhes they have made their Addreſſes and maſqued their ſelf-intereſts, if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in ſo ſhort an interim of time, at once adoring ſo many riſing Suns.</p>
            <p>Since I have ſo ſtrangely diſſgreſſed, it will not be amiſs to take notice of a Book lately come forth, intituled, <hi>Hiſtory and Policy reviewed,</hi> concerning the political tranſactions of the Protector, publiſh'd in a ſtrange name, written in the ſtile of the holy Court, in which, the Author under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes a prodigious Enterprize, to compare <hi>Cromwel</hi> to <hi>Moſes;</hi> his Pen is too palpably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aught with Flattery, yet not without un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Subtilty; he having like the little <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Gentleman, in the ſhort Jacket,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:54496:27"/>pickt the Vermin out of <hi>Nic. Machiavels</hi> Head for his uſe; throwing off one ſide principles honeſter then his own; <hi>Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi> never ſo diſguiſing himſelf with the Vizard of Religion, that he appears to be an arranter Devil than the <hi>Florentine;</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain I am, that I never read a Book that more pleaſed or diſpleaſed me.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, at his firſt inſtalment, <hi>Heavens bleſs us,</hi> immediately follows a Plot, miraculouſly diſcovered, eleven of the grand Conſpirators being apprehended, were committed to the <hi>Tower;</hi> where hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing remained a while, they were again ſet at Liberty. This web was not well ſpun, his Spies and Informers which he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at vaſt expence, put on their Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles that they might ſee better againſt the next occaſion.</p>
            <p>In the Interim, the Scots under the Earls of <hi>Glencarne</hi> and <hi>Kenmore,</hi> raiſed another Army of 4000 Horſe and Foot, but were ſoon diſſipated by the vigilancy of Colonel <hi>Morgan,</hi> who after a ſhort but ſmart Fight, killed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one hundred and fifty of them, and defeated all the reſt. Suſpicions are neceſſary Alarms, as they at leaſt ſuffer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons not to be overtaken with too much ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of their Affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:54496:28"/>
               <hi>Another great Plot</hi> was now again diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; the chief Conſpirators were ſaid to be Mr. <hi>Thomas</hi> and <hi>John Gerrard,</hi> Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>John Jones</hi> an Apothecary, and <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Tendor, Somerſet Fox,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Peter Vowel;</hi> who were all condemned, but two only ſuffered, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Vowel</hi> who was hanged. Alſo about the ſame time the Portugal Ambaſſadors Brother was brought to his Tryal for the piſtoling of one Mr. <hi>Greenwood</hi> by a Knight of <hi>Malta,</hi> one of his high ſpirited followers; the tumult be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afterwards occaſion'd from his retinue, he having been firſt very uncivilly treated by Mr. <hi>Gerrard</hi> in his expatiating of the <hi>New Exchange,</hi> as he termed it in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration; for which Mr. <hi>Gerrard</hi> received a prick with his Dagger, and afterwards had the honour to die the ſame Death. The young unfortunate Stranger ſuffered a very high favour to pleaſe the <hi>New Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</hi> Chevaliers.</p>
            <p>Mean while the Scotch Highlanders im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patint of bearing the Engliſh yoke, reſolved to try the other bout; to which purpoſe, they aſſembled together in great Numbers, having General <hi>Middleton</hi> to their Leader, who was newly come to them out of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but all their endeavours vaniſhed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Smoak, General <hi>Monk</hi> on the twentieth
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:54496:28"/>
               <hi>July,</hi> 1654, at a place called <hi>Loughberry,</hi> gave them ſuch a charge as utterly defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, and made them incapable of ever after thinking of appearing in Arms again.</p>
            <p>Soon after was a Parliament called, who no ſooner were ſet, but fell upon queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Power by which they were convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated; and doubting of its lawfulneſs were ſoon diſſolved by the ſame Power which they diſtruſted. The Protector at the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of this ſhort Parliament, made a very long Speech, wherein amongſt many other paſſages he hath this expreſſion; <hi>This one thing I ſpeak as thus adviſed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, as having been to this Day of this Opinion, and this have been my conſtant Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, well known to many that hear me ſpeak, if this one thing had been inſerted, that one thing, that this Government ſhould have been, and placed in my Family hereditary, I would have rejected it.</hi> And a little after, <hi>If this be of humane ſtructure, and invention, and it be an old plotting and contrivance to bring things to this iſſue, and that they are not the births of Providence, then they will come to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding his Speech was can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died over with Scripture phraſes, and great expreſſions of his zeal for the good Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Land; yet theſe his Actings
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54496:29"/>much diſcontented the common People, whereupon enſued riſings in <hi>Shropſhire, Montgomery, Nottinghamſhire, Northumber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> but the moſt conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble was at <hi>Salisbury,</hi> where Sir <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſeph Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaff, Penruddock,</hi> and <hi>Jones,</hi> who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly been Officers in the late King's Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, having gotten together about 200 arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed-Men, entered <hi>Salisbury,</hi> ſeized on all the Inns and chief Houſes; and the Aſſizes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing holden there at that time, they took a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Judges Commiſſions and Pattents, and all their Horſes, and ſo marched away. Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby</hi> and Sir <hi>Richard Mallever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> aſſembled ſome Forces alſo in <hi>Yorkſhire;</hi> but not being ſeconded according to their expectation, they diſperſt themſelves on their own account. For theſe actings were put to Death Maſter <hi>Lucas, Thorp, Kenſey, Graves,</hi> and <hi>Penruddock,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby</hi> was taken and Impriſoned, and aftewards beheaded upon another account, as I ſhall ſhow you in its due place. About this time the great Head-piece of <hi>Europe</hi> joyns his Foxes Tail to our Lions Skin; Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies are held betwixt the French and us, which occaſioning ſome Jealouſies with ſome other bitter Pills that had before been ſwallowed, but not diſgeſted by the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, cauſed ſome Heart-burnings, which
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54496:29"/>ſoon broke forth into an open War, firſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged by the Generals, <hi>Pen</hi> and <hi>Venables,</hi> who on the 27. of <hi>December</hi> 1654, with a gallant Fleet ſet ſail from <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> and on the 28 of <hi>January</hi> following, arrived at the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> where they ſeized on 18 <hi>Holland</hi> Merchant Men, who contrary to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the long Parliament traffiqued in thoſe Parts, from thence they ſailed to <hi>Hiſpaniola,</hi> arriving near to the Port <hi>Sancta Domingo,</hi> where by the deepneſs of Sands, and heat of the Climate being infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely tired, they were by the Spaniards put to Flight, and enforced to march back again to their Ships; from thence they ſet-ſail to the Iſland of <hi>Jama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca,</hi> which after a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reſiſtance they maſtered, and have ſince preſerved, notwithſtanding the Spaniards to regain the ſame, landed there with two or three thouſand Men, but were diſcomſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Loſs of all their Cannon and Baggage.</p>
            <p>In the Interim General <hi>Blake</hi> with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Fleet of Ships, having caſt Anchor before <hi>Tunis, April,</hi> 18, 1655. ſent unto the Dey of the Place, demanding ſatisfaction for ſome Engliſh Ships, which the Pyrates of thoſe parts had carried away, and the Liberty of the Engliſh Slaves they had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained; but his meſſage and himſelf was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54496:30"/>with ſcorn and deriſion, the <hi>Turk</hi> making this anſwer, <hi>Behold our Caſtles of</hi> Galleta, <hi>and our Caſtles and Veſſels of</hi> Port<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ferino, <hi>do your worſt againſt them, and do no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> think to brave us with the ſight of your grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Fleet.</hi> This anſwer ſo exaſperated the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Admiral, that notwithſtanding there were one hundred and twenty Guns plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Shore, and in the Caſtle againſt them; yet regardleſs of all danger, he ſet upon their Men of War which lay in <hi>Port<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ferino,</hi> and in leſs then in four Hours ſpace burnt all their Ships, being in number nine to their very Keels, which enforced the King of <hi>Tunis</hi> to ſeek to the Engliſh for their friendſhip, and reſtored all the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for little or nothing.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſucceſſes were ſeconded by two other great Victories obtained over th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Spaniards at Sea; the one by Genera <hi>Mountague</hi> about nine Leagues from <hi>Cadiz</hi> where he deſtroyed ſix of their Ship whereof two were taken, two run aground one ſunk, and another burnt, and there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Marqueſs of <hi>Badex,</hi> his Wife and Daughter; the young Marqueſs and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Brother, with a great deal of Wealth bei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taken, and brought into <hi>England.</hi> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Fight being incomparably related by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Laureat of our times, I thought fit to inſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:54496:30"/>it, not to deprive the Reader of ſo Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant a Poem; let him wave the poetical Flattery of it as he pleaſes.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>Upon the preſent War with <hi>Spain,</hi> and the firſt Victory obtained at Sea.</head>
               <l>NOw for ſome Ages had the Pride of <hi>Spain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Made the Sun ſhine on half th' world invain;</l>
               <l>While ſhe bid War to to all that durſt ſupply</l>
               <l>The place of thoſe, her Cruelty made dye.</l>
               <l>Of Nature's Bounty Men forbear to taſte,</l>
               <l>And the beſt Portion of the Earth lay waſte.</l>
               <l>From the <hi>New World</hi> her Silver and her Gold,</l>
               <l>Came like a Tempeſt, to confound the Old.</l>
               <l>Feeding with theſe the brib'd <hi>Elector's</hi> Hopes,</l>
               <l>She made at Pleaſure Emperors and Popes:</l>
               <l>With theſe, advancing her unjuſt Deſigns,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Europe</hi> was ſhaken with her Indian Mines.</l>
               <l>When our <hi>Protector</hi> looking with diſdain</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this gilded Majeſty of <hi>Spain;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And knowing well that Empire muſt decline,</l>
               <l>Whoſe chief ſupport, and ſinews, are of Coyn:</l>
               <l>Our Nation's ſolid vertue, did oppoſe</l>
               <l>To the rich Troublers of the World's repoſe.</l>
               <l>And now ſome months encamping on the main,</l>
               <l>Our Naval Army had beſieged <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They that the whole Worlds Monarchy deſign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Are to their Ports by our bold Fleet confin'd:</l>
               <l>From whence our <hi>Red Croſs</hi> they triumphant ſee,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:54496:31"/>
Riding without a Rival on the Sea,</l>
               <l>Others may uſe the Ocean as their road,</l>
               <l>Only the Engliſh make it their abode:</l>
               <l>Whoſe ready Sails with every Wind can flie,</l>
               <l>And make a covenant with th' unconſtant Skie.</l>
               <l>Our Oaks ſecure, as if they there took root;</l>
               <l>We tread on Billows with a ſteady foot.</l>
               <l>Mean while the Spaniards in <hi>America,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Near to the Line, the Sun approaching ſaw;</l>
               <l>And hop'd their European Coaſts to find</l>
               <l>Cleard from our Ships, by the Autumnal Wind.</l>
               <l>Their huge capacious Gallions ſtuft with Plate,</l>
               <l>The labouring Winds drives ſlowly towards their Fate.</l>
               <l>Before Saint <hi>Lucar</hi> they their Guns diſcharge,</l>
               <l>To tell their Joy, or to invite a Barge,</l>
               <l>This heard, ſome Ships of ours, tho' out of view,</l>
               <l>As ſwift as Eagles to the Quarry flew.</l>
               <l>So heedleſs Lambs which for their Mothers bleat,</l>
               <l>Wake hungry Lions and become their Meat.</l>
               <l>Arriv'd, they ſoon begin that Tragick Play,</l>
               <l>And with their ſmoaky Cannon baniſh Day.</l>
               <l>Night, horrour, ſlaughter, with confuſion meets,</l>
               <l>And in their ſable Arms embrace the Fleets.</l>
               <l>Through yielding Planks the angry Bullets fly,</l>
               <l>And of one Wound hundreds together die.</l>
               <l>Born under different Stars, one Fate they have,</l>
               <l>The Ship their Coffin, and the Sea their Grave.</l>
               <l>Bold were the Men, which on the Ocean firſt</l>
               <l>Spread their new Sails, ſhipwreck was the worſt</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:54496:31"/>
More danger now from Men alone we find,</l>
               <l>Then from the Rocks, the Billows, or the Wind.</l>
               <l>They that had ſail'd from the Antartick Pole,</l>
               <l>Their Treaſure ſafe, and all their Veſſels whole;</l>
               <l>In ſight of their dear Country ruin'd be,</l>
               <l>Without the guilt of either Rock or <hi>Sea.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What they would ſpare, our fiercer Art deſtroys,</l>
               <l>Excelling ſtorms in terror and in noiſe.</l>
               <l>Once <hi>love</hi> from <hi>Hyda</hi> did both Hoſts ſurvey,</l>
               <l>And when he pleas'd to thunder, part the Fray:</l>
               <l>Here Heaven in vain that kind retreat ſhould ſound,</l>
               <l>The louder Cannon had the Thunder drown'd.</l>
               <l>Some we made Prize while others burnt and rent,</l>
               <l>With their rich Lading to the bottom went.</l>
               <l>Down ſinks at once (ſo fortunate with us ſports)</l>
               <l>The Pay of Armies, and the Pride of Courts.</l>
               <l>Vain Man, whoſe rage buries as low that ſtore,</l>
               <l>As Avarice, had digg'd for it before.</l>
               <l>What Earth in her dark Bowels could not keep,</l>
               <l>From greedy hands, lles ſafer in the deep:</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Thetis</hi> kindly doth from Mortals hide</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſeeds of Luxury Debate, and Pride,</l>
               <l>And now into her lap the richeſt Prize.</l>
               <l>Fell, with the nobleſt of our Enemies.</l>
               <l>The Marqueſs glad to ſee the Fire deſtroy</l>
               <l>Wealth, that prevailing Fees were to enjoy:</l>
               <l>Out from his flaming Ship his Children ſent,</l>
               <l>To periſh in a milder Element.</l>
               <l>Then laid him by his burning Ladies ſide,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:54496:32"/>
And ſince he could not ſave her, with her dy'd.</l>
               <l>Spices and Gums about them melting fry,</l>
               <l>And Phenix-like, in that rich neſt they die.</l>
               <l>Death bitter is, for what we leave behind,</l>
               <l>But taking with us, all we love, is kind,</l>
               <l>What could he more then hold for term of Life,</l>
               <l>His Indian Treaſure, and his more priz'd Wife?</l>
               <l>Alive, in Flames of equal love they burn'd,</l>
               <l>And now together are to Aſhes turn'd.</l>
               <l>Aſhes more worth then all their Funerals coſt,</l>
               <l>Then the huge Treaſure which was with them loſt.</l>
               <l>Theſe dying Lovers, and their floating Sons,</l>
               <l>Suſpend the Fight, and ſilence all our Guns.</l>
               <l>Beauty and Youth, about to periſh, finds</l>
               <l>Such noble pity in brave Engliſh minds;</l>
               <l>That the rich Spoil neglecting, and the Prize,</l>
               <l>All labour now to ſave their Enemies.</l>
               <l>How frail our paſſion's? how ſoon changed are</l>
               <l>Our wrath and Fury to a friendly care?</l>
               <l>They that but know to gain the Spaniſh Plate,</l>
               <l>Made the Sea bluſh with Blood, forget their hate;</l>
               <l>And their young Foes, while ſinking they retrive,</l>
               <l>With greater danger then they fought they dive.</l>
               <l>With theſe returns Victorious <hi>Mountague,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With Lawrel in his Hands, and half <hi>Perue.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let the brave General divide that Bough.</l>
               <l>Our great Protector hath ſuch Wreaths enough,</l>
               <l>His conquering head hath no more room for bays</l>
               <l>Then let it be as the whole Nation prays:</l>
               <l>Let the rich Oar forthwith be melted down,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:54496:32"/>
And the State fixt, by making him a Crown:</l>
               <l>With Ermins clad, and Purple; let him hold</l>
               <l>A Royal Scepter made of Spaniſh Gold.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>About this time the blaſphemies of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Sectaries in <hi>England</hi> were horrible; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of one <hi>James Nailor,</hi> who under a ſeeming Sanctity, and pretended illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, vented moſt horrible blaſphemies, for which he was caſt into <hi>Exceſter</hi> Goal; yet had this wretched Impoſtor ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched his followers to the committing of ſtrange abſurdities, that they aſcribed to him Divine Honours, and gave him in Scripture phraſe, the ſame titles which are applicable to none but Chriſt himſelf.</p>
            <p>In a Letter of one <hi>Richard Fairman</hi> to him, are theſe horrid expreſſions, <q>I am fil'd with joy and rejoycing when I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thee in the eternal Unity. O my Soul is melting within me, when I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thy Beauty and Innocency, dear and precious Son of <hi>Zion,</hi> whoſe Mother is a Virgin, and whoſe Birth is immortal.</q> 
               <hi>One of his ſhe Converts writes of him thus,</hi> 
               <q>All the Wiſe Men ſhall ſeek for him, and when they have found him, they ſhall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen their Ears, and ſhall give unto him of their Gold, Frankincenſe, and Myrrh. </q>
               <hi>The ſame Woman in another Letter to him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds thus.</hi> 
               <q>O thou faireſt of ten thouſand,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:54496:33"/>thou only begotten Son of God, how my Heart panteth after thee; O ſtay me with Flaggons, and comfort me with Wine; my well-beloved thou art like a Roe, or young Hart, upon the Mountains of Spices.</q> 
               <hi>Then by way of Poſtſcript her Husband</hi> Thomas Stranger <hi>adds this.</hi> 
               <q>Thy Name is no more to be called <hi>James,</hi> but <hi>Jeſus.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>Alſo a Maid named</hi> Dorcas Erbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>being examined, declared,</hi> 
               <q>
                  <hi>James Nailor</hi> to be the holy one of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the only Son of God,</q> and that ſhe pulled off his Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and put her Cloaths under his Feet, becauſe he is the Holy Lord, of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and that ſhe knew no other Saviour but him; affirming moreover, that the Spirit of the Lord within her, commanded her to call him Lord and Maſter, and to ſerve him. That in <hi>Exceſter</hi> Goal he had raiſed her from the Dead, after ſhe had been dead two Days, and that he ſhould ſit at the Right Hand of the Father, and judge the World.</p>
            <p>Having ſeduced theſe ſilly Souls into ſuch damnable opinions, and gotten releaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment out of <hi>Exceſter</hi> Goal, he began imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dintely to play his Pranks at divers Places in the Weſt; particularly at <hi>Wells</hi> and <hi>Glaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenbury,</hi> thorow which Towns he rode on Horſeback, a Man going bare before him,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:54496:33"/>ſome walking a foot on each ſide of his Stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup, and others ſtrewing their Garments in the Way; from thence he took his Journey towards <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and coming to a Village called <hi>Bedminſter,</hi> about a Mile from <hi>Briſtol,</hi> rid through it in the ſame preſumptuous blaſphemous manner, as he did before at <hi>Wells</hi> and <hi>Glaſtenbury.</hi> There accompanied him two Men, with each a Woman behind on Horſeback, which alighted when they came to the Suburbs of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and footed it along on each ſide of <hi>Nailor</hi>'s Horſe, the Man ſtill bare-headed leading the Horſe, and all the Way they went, they ſung, <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy Lord God of Iſrael,</hi> and then the Women led the Horſe with the Reins in their Hands, up to the high Croſs of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and from thence to the White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hart-Inn in <hi>Broad-ſtreet;</hi> by this time the Magiſtrates hearing of their doings, ſent for <hi>Nailor</hi> and his Companions, who came ſinging all the Way <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> and <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy,</hi> &amp;c. The Magiſtrates of <hi>Briſtol</hi> having examined him, ſent him up to the Parliament (together with the narrative of his Action committed in thoſe parts) to receive his Sentence, which was as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</p>
            <p>
               <q>That <hi>James Nailor</hi> be ſet with his Head in the Pillory, in the new <hi>Palace</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:54496:34"/>at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> during the ſpace of two Hours, on <hi>Thurſday</hi> next, and ſhall be whipped by the Hangman through the Streets from <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to the <hi>Old Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change London;</hi> and there likewiſe be ſet in the Pillory, for the ſpace of two Hours, between the Hours of eleven and one, on <hi>Saturday</hi> next; in each of the ſaid Places, wearing a Paper containing an Inſcription of his Crimes, and at the <hi>Old Exchange</hi> his Tongue ſhall be bored through with a hot Iron; and that he be there alſo ſtigmatized in the Forehead with the Letter B. and that he be afterwards ſent to <hi>Briſtol,</hi> and conveyed into, and thro' the ſaid City on a Horſe bare ridg'd, with his Face back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; and there alſo publickly whip'd, the next Market-day after he comes thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. That from thence he be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to priſon in <hi>Bridewell, London,</hi> and there reſtrained from the Society of all People, and kept to hard labour, till he ſhall be releaſed by Parliament; and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that time be debarred the uſe of Pen, Ink, and Paper, and ſhall have no relief, but what he earns by his daily Labour, which accordingly was executed upon him, <hi>December</hi> 17. 1656.</q>
            </p>
            <p>His Flies and Familiars were ſtill uſeful to him for the diſcovering of more ſtrange
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54496:34"/>deſigns; the revealing of which, no Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on kept many Conſpiracies from being at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted, to which effect there is yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Plot, againſt the Protectors Life, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by <hi>Miles Sindercomb,</hi> alias <hi>Fiſh,</hi> one who had formerly been a Parliament Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, under the command of Sir <hi>John Rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds,</hi> together with one <hi>Cecil;</hi> induced thereunto, as is ſaid by <hi>Don Alonſo,</hi> the late <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſador; to the effecting their deſigns, they are ſaid to have hired a Houſe at <hi>Hammerſmith,</hi> adjoining by the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way ſide, to have ſhot him in his Coach, as he paſſed by; but that failing, they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to have ſhot him in <hi>Hide-Park,</hi> and to that purpoſe they filed off the Hinges of the Gates for their better eſcape; and this miſcarrying, they intended to have fired <hi>White Hall.</hi> For theſe Offences <hi>Sinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb</hi> was arraigned at the Upper Bench Bar in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall, February,</hi> 9. 1656. where being found guilty by the Jury, he was condemned to be hanged, drawn, and quartered at <hi>Tyburn;</hi> but before his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he was found dead in his Bed, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral preſumptions of a violent Death ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing on him; it was concluded he poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned himſelf. Afterwards he was drawn from the Tower unto Tower-hill, at a Horſe's-Tail, with his Head forward, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:54496:35"/>there under the Scaffold, turned into a hole ſtark naked, and a Stake ſpiked and plated with Iron, driven thro' him into the Earth. It is to be obſerved that whatſoever the vigilancy of the Guard of the Tower was over this Gentleman, that he died with as freſh a Colour as Sir <hi>Thomas Overbury</hi> is ſaid to have expired with.</p>
            <p>But to return where we left, that ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sea-man General <hi>Blake,</hi> the Protectors intended <hi>Drake,</hi> an honeſt ſtout incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sea-man, he failing with his Fleet to <hi>Sancta Cruza,</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Teneriff,</hi> in which Port lay ſixteen great <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Veſſels, laden with rich Merchandizes from the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> He on the 20th of <hi>April,</hi> 1657. ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and deſtroyed them all, not ſixty of his own Men being loſt.</p>
            <p>But to return, <hi>June</hi> the 20. 1657 the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector with great Magnificence was inſtalled at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the Parliament then ſitting; and in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> a rich Cloth of State was ſet up, and under it a Chair of State placed upon an aſcent of two degrees, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Carpets, and before it a Table with a Chair appointed for the Speaker of the Parliament, and on each ſide of the Hall upon the ſaid Structure were Seats raiſed one above another, and decently covered for the Members of Parliament, and below
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54496:35"/>them, Seats on one ſide for the Judges of the Land, and on the other ſide for the Aldermen of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About two of the Clock in the Afternoon, the Protector met the Parliament in the Painted Chamber, and paſſed ſuch Bills as were preſented to him; after which they went in order to the place appointed in <hi>Weſtminſter Hall;</hi> the Protector ſtanding under the Cloth of Eſtate, the Lord <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> Speaker of the Parliament, addreſt himſelf to him in this Speech.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>May it pleaſe your Highneſs,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>You are now upon a great Theatre, in a large Chore of People, you have the Parliament of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>before you; on your Right Hand my Lords the Judges, and on your Left-Hand, the Lord Mayor, Aldermen and Sheriffs of</hi> London; <hi>the moſt noble and populous City of</hi> England. <hi>The Parliament, with the Interpoſition of your ſufferage, makes Laws, and the Judges, and Governours of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>are the great Diſpencers of thoſe Laws to the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Occaſion of this great Convention and Intercourſe, is, to give an Inveſtiture to your Highneſs in that eminent Place of</hi> Lord Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector; <hi>a Name you had before, but it is now ſettled by the full and unanimous conſent of the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54496:36"/>People of theſe three Nations aſſembled in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament; you have no new Name, but a new date added to the old Name; the</hi> 16 <hi>of</hi> Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>is now changed to the</hi> 26 <hi>of</hi> June.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am commanded by the Parliament, to make oblation to your Highneſs of four Things in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to this Inauguration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt is a Robe of Purple, an Emblem of Magiſtracy, and imports Righteouſneſs and Juſtice; when you have put on the Veſtment, I may ſay, (and I hope without Offence) that you are a Gown Man. This Robe is of a mixt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, to ſhew the mixture of Juſtice and Mercy, which are then moſt excellent when they are well tempered together. Juſtice without Mercy, is Wormwood and Bitterneſs, and Mercy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Juſtice is of a too ſoft a Temper for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for a Magiſtrate muſt have two Hands,</hi> Plectentem &amp; Amplectentem.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The next thing is a Bible, a Book that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains the Holy Scripture; in which you have the Honour and Happineſs to be well verſed. This is the Book of Life, conſiſting of two Teſtaments, the Old and New. In the firſt we have</hi> Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum velatum, <hi>Chriſt in Types, Shadows, and Figures; in the latter we have</hi> Chriſtum reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum, <hi>Chriſt revealed. This Book carries in it the grounds of the true Chriſtian Proteſtant Religion; it's a Book of Books, it contains in it both precepts and examples for good Government.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:54496:36"/>
Alexander <hi>ſo highly valued the Books of his Maſter</hi> Ariſtotle, <hi>and other great Princes other Books, that they have laid them every Night under their Pillows. Theſe are all but Legends and Romances to this one Book; at Book to be had always in remembrance: I find it ſaid in a Part of this Book which I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to read, and it is this.</hi> Deut. 17. And it ſhall be when he ſitteth upon the Throne of his Kingdom, that he ſhall write a Copy of this Law in a Book, out of that which is before the Prieſts and Levites. And it ſhall be with him, and he ſhall read therein all the Days of his Life, that he may learn to fear the Lord God, and to keep all the Words of his Law and thoſe Statutes, to do them. That his Heart be not lifted up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his Brethren; and that he turn not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide from the Commandment, to the Right Hand or to the Left, to the end he may prolong his Days in his Kingdom, he and his Children in the midſt of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The next Thing that I am to offer to your Highneſs, is a Scepter, not unlike a Staff, for you are to be a Staff to the Weak and Poor; it's of ancient uſe in this kind; it's ſaid in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, in reference to</hi> Judah, <hi>the Royal Tribe,</hi> That the Scepter ſhall not depart from <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah. It was of like uſe in other Kingdoms and Governments.</hi> Homer <hi>the Prince of the Greek
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54496:37"/>Poets, calls Kings and Princes Scepter-bearers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The laſt Thing is a Sword, not a Military, but a Civil Sword; a Sword rather for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence than an Offence; not to defend your ſelf only, but others alſo; the Sword is an Emblem of Juſtice. The noble Lord</hi> Talbot, <hi>in</hi> Henry <hi>the Sixths time, wrote upon his Sword,</hi> Ego ſum <hi>Talboti,</hi> propter occidendum inimicos meos; <hi>This Gallant Lord was a better Souldier then a Critick. If I might preſume to fix a Motto upon this Sword, it ſhould be this,</hi> Ego ſum Demini Protectoris ad protegendum populum meum.</p>
            <q>
               <p>I ſay, this Sword is an Emblem of Juſtice, and is to be uſed as King <hi>Solomon</hi> uſed his, for the diſcovery of truth in the points of Juſtice. I may ſay of this Sword as King <hi>David</hi> ſaid of <hi>Goliah</hi>'s Sword, <hi>There is none like this,</hi> Juſtice is the proper Vertue of the Imperial Throne, and by Juſtice the Thrones of Kings and Princes are eſtabliſhed. Juſtice is a Royal Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which as one ſaith of it, doth employ the other three Cardinal Vertues in her ſervice. 1. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> to diſcern the nocent from the Innocent. 2. <hi>Fortitude,</hi> to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, and execute. 3. <hi>Temperance,</hi> ſo to carry Juſtice that Paſſion be no ingredient, and that it be without confuſion, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:54496:37"/>
You have given ample Teſtimony in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> theſe particulars; ſo that this Sword in your Hand will be a right Sword of Juſtice, attended with <hi>Wiſdom, Fortitude,</hi> and <hi>Temperance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you have all theſe together, what a comely and glorious fight is it to behold, <hi>A Lord Protector in a Purple Robe, with a Scepter in his Hand, a Sword of Juſtice girt about him, and his Eyes fixt upon the Bible.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Long may you proſperouſly enjoy them all, to your own comfort, and the comfort of the People of theſe three Nations.</p>
            <p>The Speech being ended, Maſter Speaker came from his Chair, took the Robe, and therewith veſted the Protector, being aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein by the Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi> the Lord <hi>Whitlock</hi> and others. Which done, the Bible was delivered him; after that the Sword girt about him; and laſt of all he had the Scepter delivered him. Theſe Things being performed, Maſter Speaker re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned unto his Chair, and adminiſtred him his Oath, <hi>in haec verba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I do in the Preſence, and by the Name of God Almighty, promiſe and ſwear, that to the uttermoſt of my Power I will uphold and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the true Reformed Proteſtant Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54496:38"/>in the Purity thereof, as it is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament to the uttermoſt of my Power and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; and encourage the Profeſſion and Profeſſors of the ſame; and that to the utmoſt of my Power I will endeavour as Chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate of theſe three Nations, the Maintenance and Preſervation of the Peace and Safety, and juſt Rights and Priviledge of the People thereof; and ſhall in all Things, according to our beſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt Knowledge and Power, govern the People of theſe three Nations according to Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Ceremonies being performed, a Herald of Arms by ſound of Trumpet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed him, <hi>Lord Protector of England, Scotland, Ireland, and the Dominions thereto belonging;</hi> hereupon the Trumpets ſounded again, and the People (after the uſual man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) gave ſeveral Acclamations, with loud ſhouts, crying, <hi>God ſave the Lord Protector.</hi> His Highneſs had ſcarce accepted of theſe Honours, but as if the ill affected would not let him breath, <hi>yet another Plot</hi> is diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, Collonel <hi>Edward Sexby</hi> is ſaid to have conſpired againſt the Lord Protector; for which he was committed to the <hi>Tower,</hi> where having continued about half a Year, he died.</p>
            <p>But to reflect a little back, <hi>Mazarine</hi> that great Miniſter of State, on which hinge all
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54496:38"/>the grand Affairs of <hi>France</hi> turn, perfects a Peace with <hi>England;</hi> the Protector having no regard to thoſe Advantages that <hi>Spain</hi> might render him as to Commerce, the Places of Hoſtage which ſhe proffered to put into his Hands, as <hi>Gravelin Dunkirk,</hi> and others, he was ſwayed with other Intereſt which he beſt underſtood himſelf, to prefer an Alliance and League with <hi>France</hi> before all thoſe Advantages, except his civility in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd him (which ſeldom had ſuch Power over him) to look more lovingly upon <hi>France</hi> as the weakeſt at that time, being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned by ſome of her Allies, as quite diſordered by an Inteſtine War in her own Bowels, her Navigation totally ruined, as the Pirates of <hi>Dunkirk</hi> had blockt up all her Sea Ports; whereas the Engliſh ſcowred thoſe Seas, caſt away the Pyrates, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the <hi>Mounſieur</hi> and <hi>Diego</hi> by their ſucceſſes to their ſo likely advantageous Peace. Indeed, (as one writes) it was a high generoſity, ſince the Engliſh cauſed the French to loſe <hi>Graveling</hi> and <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> to help <hi>France</hi> again to take thoſe places. In the mean Space was not here rare bandying of Intereſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France</hi> having thus perfected a Peace with <hi>England,</hi> they joyntly reſolve to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainſt the Spaniard; hereupon Article<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:54496:39"/>
               <hi>Reynolds</hi> with ſix thouſand Foot was ſent into <hi>Picardy,</hi> to joyn with the French Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valry, which compleated as gallant an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my as had been ſeen in <hi>France</hi> for many Years together. Theſe jointly beſiege and take <hi>Mardike;</hi> a ſtrong Fort of the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards in <hi>Flanders,</hi> whereof Major General <hi>Morgan</hi> took Poſſeſſion for the Engliſh; as the earneſt of further Conqueſts; which the Spaniards attempting for to regain, were twice repulſed with very great loſs.</p>
            <p>But the Joy of theſe Succeſſes was miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated by the Death of Admiral <hi>Blake,</hi> who as he got his Honour by the Sea, died on it, and that within ſight of <hi>Plimouth.</hi> He was a Man who had deſerved of his Country, and might juſtly be ſtiled the <hi>Neptune</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. His Body was brought with a Naval pomp by Water from <hi>Greenwich</hi> to <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> being a ſuitable Ceremony to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and was there buried in <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh's Chappel. Upon whom an Ingenious Perſon beſtowed this Epitaph.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Here lies a Man, made <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> ſhake</l>
               <l>Made <hi>France</hi> to tremble, and the Turks to quake.</l>
               <l>Thus he tam'd Men, but if a Lady ſtood</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſight, it rais'd a Palſie in his blood;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> agoniſt, who in his Life</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:54496:39"/>
Had Fortune as familiar as a Wife.</l>
               <l>A ſtiff hard Iron Souldier; for he</l>
               <l>It ſeems had more of <hi>Mars</hi> than <hi>Mercury;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At Sea he thundered, calm'd each raging Wave,</l>
               <l>And now he's dead, ſent thundring to his Grave.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Soon after was St. <hi>Venant</hi> taken by the Engliſh, the Lord <hi>Henry Cromwel</hi> made De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Sir <hi>John Reynolds,</hi> Collonel <hi>White,</hi> and ſome other Officers drowned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Goodwin Sands,</hi> as they were coming out of <hi>Flanders</hi> into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One writes that the ſubtilty of diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Plots, though but in the <hi>Embrio,</hi> or before they are hatcht, in the time of Peace is the moſt ſuccinct way of letting of Blood? March 24. (the laſt Day of the Year account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for) 1657. a great Conſpiracy was again diſcovered in <hi>London,</hi> ſeveral Regiments (as was ſaid) being enrolled; who on the firſt day of <hi>May</hi> in the Night Time ſhould have ſet Fire on ſeveral parts of the City, and whilſt the Confuſion and Horrour thereof had ſeized all Men, they ſhould have made a general maſſacre of all who oppoſed them. Hereupon ſeveral Perſons were apprehended, as Doctor <hi>Hewet,</hi> Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby,</hi> Collonel <hi>Aſhton,</hi> &amp;c. and a High Court of Juſtice e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected for the Tryal of them; and firſt they began with Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby,</hi> the Articles
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:54496:40"/>charged againſt them will in part diſcover themſelves in their ſeveral Speeches made juſt before their Deaths. In ſhort, they were both condemned, Dr. <hi>Hewet</hi> (profeſſing himſelf to be ignorant of ſuch Law; tho' amongſt the moſt learned Divines few of them were more knowing in the Goſpel) being taken in three defaults upon formali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Court, was proceeded againſt as mute,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> 8. 1658. was the Day appointed for their beheading, Sir <hi>Henry Slingsby</hi> firſt mounting the Stage, ſpake in effect as followeth.</p>
            <p>That he ſtood condemned by the Court of Juſtice, as contriving and endeavouring to withdraw divers Officers of the Garriſon of <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Hull</hi> from their Duty; and perſwading them to a ſurrendring and yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up of that Garriſon, and one that held correſpondence with ſome beyond Sea to that end. That it was true, he had confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence upon that Account with the Officers of that Garriſon; and that he gave Major <hi>Waterhouſe</hi> a Commiſſion ſigned <hi>Charles R.</hi> But that it was but an old one that had lain by him, though he thought fit to make uſe of it to the Major. Many Paſſages he ſaid there were which he would not inſiſt on; that ſome Friends of his had made Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54496:40"/>to his Highneſs for the ſaving of his Life, but it ſeems it was thought fit not to be granted, and therefore he ſubmitted, and was ready to dye, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Having uttered theſe and the like Words he took off a Ring from his Bandſtrings wherein inſtead of a Seal engraven, was the Picture of the late King exactly done, and giving it to a Gentleman that ſtood by him, he ſaid, <hi>Pray give this to</hi> Harry. Then he addreſt himſelf to Prayer, wherein he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſome time; taking leave of his Friends, he ſubmitted his Neck to the Block, and had his Head ſevered from his Body at one Blow by the Executioner. This at one Blow by the Executioner, the Reader may obſerve hath been very often repeated in this Volume.</p>
            <p>His Tragick Scene being acted, that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and Reverend Divine Doctor <hi>Hewet,</hi> the golden tongu'd <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> entered the Liſts of Death. In this Warfare the Doctor put on the ſpiritual Armour of a bleſſed Confidence, delivering his Mind to the People in theſe following Words.</p>
            <p>I am now become a publick Spectacle to Men and Angels, and (I hope) God who is omniſcient is now beholding me with much Pity, Mercy and Compaſſion; and the more, becauſe I am now come to that end
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54496:41"/>that his own Son came into the World to, to bear Witneſs to the Truth; he himſelf ſaid, <hi>For this end was I born, for this cauſe came I into the World, that I ſhould bear Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Truth.</hi> I was brought into the World (the Chriſtian World) for to bear Witneſs to the Truth of the Goſpel, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> common Chriſtian; I was brought into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> World (the Church) as a Miniſter of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bleſſed Word and Sacraments; [bleſſed be his Name for that great Honour and Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;] and I came into the World to dy more immediately for the Teſtimony of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, which God hath now called me to. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> came into this World (this Commonwealth) to be a Member thereof, to bear Witneſs to the Truths of the Cuſtoms, the Laws the Liberties, and Priviledges thereof; fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> am a Member of the Common-wealth. And methinks it ſeems to me a ſtrange thing that in as much as we all plead for Liberty and Priviledges, and I pleading for the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, the Laws, the Statutes, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cuſtoms of this Land, yet I ſhould die by thoſe that ſhould ſtand for the Laws, the Statutes, and Priviledges of the Land. An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I am here beheld by thoſe that plead for their Liberties, and I hope I am pittied, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I here give up my ſelf willingly and ſteely to be a State-Martyr for the publick
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54496:41"/>good; and I had rather die many Deaths my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elf, then betray my fellow Freemen to ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any Inconveniencies that they might be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke to ſuffer, by being ſubject to the Wills <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f them that willed me to this Death.</p>
            <p>And it is worthy Remembrance that Maſter <hi>Solicitor</hi> having impeached me of Treaſon to the Commiſſioners of the Court <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainſt his Highneſs, I did often (when brought before thoſe Commiſſioners) plead for the Liberties of the People of <hi>England,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hough I had no Knowledge of the Law, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et I had Inſtructions from thoſe that were learned in the Law, and had ſeveral Law-Caſes and made my Appeal. Firſt, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Judicature that I was to be tryed by, Whether it were according to Law? Whether it were according to the Act? And whether it were according to the Words of the ſaid Act? I did appeal to have the ſaid Act argued by learned Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers on both ſides, and then to be reſolved by his Highneſs own Council, which was denied me. [This by the by.] I preſſing the Argument, made a ſecond Appeal, that thoſe Judges, if they would give ſingly their ſeveral Judgments that it was a juſt and lawful Court of Judicature, I would
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:54496:42"/>anſwer to my Charge. I did make another Appeal to thoſe that were his Highneſſes Council, and pleaded againſt me, That if they would deliver it to me under their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to be according to Law, I would then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> plead, and anſwer to the Charge. What was then ſaid further my Spirits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faint, I ſhall not ſay much, but only this, I was taken in three defaults upon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality of the Court. It ſeems it is a cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom in all Courts, (which I did not know before) that if they anſwer not the third time ſpeaking, by the Clerk, that then they are guilty of three defaults, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded againſt as mute: [I had no ſuch Knowledge of the Law.] So they found me guilty of thoſe defaults; and when I would have pleaded, and reſolved to begin to plead, I was taken from the Bar. I did the next Day make my Petition to the Court in the Painted Chamber, two Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were preſented, the ſame in effect; the former, the Title was miſtaken. Yet becauſe the Title was miſtaken, and no Anſwer given, therefore it was that another Petition was drawn up to the ſame Effect, with a new Title given, (as I remember) preſented by the Serjeant at Arms; and one writ it over in ſuch haſte, leſt they ſhould be drawn out of the Painted Chamber into
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54496:42"/>the Court, that I had not time to read it over, only I ſubſcribed my Name, and there was in the Front of the Petition a Word left out, but what the Word was, I know not; and this was taken ſo ill, as if I had put an Affront and Contempt on the Court: And it was thought they would have heard me plead; and then becauſe of that miſtake, they ſent Word, I ſhould have my Anſwer when I came into the Court, and my Anſwer was the Sentence of Condemnation. And therefore I pray with all my Soul, that God would forgive all thoſe that occaſioned the Charge to be drawn againſt me, to give ſuch unjuſt Things againſt me: I pray with all my Soul, that God would forgive all thoſe that upon ſo ſlender and ſmall Grounds adjudg'd me to dye, taking Advantage of ſuch ſimple Ignorance as I was in. And I had at the very beginning of my pleading, engaged their Honours no Advantage ſhould be taken againſt me to my Prejudice, that in as much as I underſtood nothing of the Law: And having heard that a Man in the Nicety of the Law might be loſt in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity thereof; meerly for ſpeaking a Word out of ſimple Ignorance, I made it my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to them that no Advantage might be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt me to the Prejudice of my Perſon
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54496:43"/>And there was to me a ſeeming Conſent; for the Preſident told, there ſhould be no Advantage taken againſt me; and upon theſe Conſiderations I am afraid there was too great Uncharitableneſs; but I pray God forgive them from the very bottom of my Soul, and I deſire that even thoſe that ſhed my Blood, may have the Bowels of the God of Mercy ſhed for them.</p>
            <p>And now having given you the Occaſion of my coming hither, it is fit I ſhould give you ſomewhat as concerning my ſelf as I am a Chriſtian, I thank God I was Baptized to the Holy Church, ſo I was Baptized to be a Member of the Holy Catholick Church, that is, the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which I dare ſay for Purity of Doctrine, and orderly Diſcipline, till a ſad Reformation had ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Face of the Church, and made it a querry whether it were a Church, or no; I ſay, it was more purely Divine and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical, than any other Doctrine or Church in the Chriſtian World, whether National, or Claſſical, or Congregational. And I muſt tell you, That as I am a Member of this Church, ſo I am a Member of the Holy Catholick Church, and ſhall give a moſt juſt Confeſſion of my Faith both negatively and affirmatively; negatively, I am ſo a Member of the Holy Catholick Church,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:54496:43"/>that I abhor all Sects, Schiſms, Sedition, and Tyranny in Religion. Affirmatively ſo, that as I hold Communion with, ſo I love and honour all Chriſtians in the World that love the ſame Lord Jeſus in Sincerity, and call on his Name agreeing with thoſe Truths that are abſolutely neceſſary, and clearly demonſtrated in the Word of God, both in the Old and New Teſtaments; tho' in Charity diſſenting from ſome others that are not neceſſary. And I, as I am thus a Chriſtian, I hope for Salvation through the Merits of Chriſt Jeſus; his Blood I rely on, his Merits I truſt to for the Salvation of my own Soul. Though to this Faith, good Works are neceſſary, not meritorious in us, but only made meritorious by Chriſt his Death; by his all ſufficiency, by his ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, and his righteouſneſs, they become meritorious. And truly as I am a Member of this Church, ſo I am a Member of this Community, and ſo pleaded for the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Priviledges thereof. I muſt now anſwer ſomething I am aſperſed withal in the World.</p>
            <p>They talk of ſomething of a Plot, and a Treaſonable Deſign, and that I had a great Intereſt in the Knowledge and Practice thereof, and that for the ſaving my Life, I would have diſcover'd and betray'd I cannot
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:54496:44"/>tell what: I hope my Converſation hath not been ſuch here in this City, where I have been a long Time very well known, as to make one imagine I ſhould intermeddle in ſuch an Action, and go ſo contrary to the Practice of my Profeſſion; and I hope there are none ſo uncharitable towards me, as to believe I had a Knowledge of that Deſign.</p>
            <p>Here I muſt come to particulars, for a Plot, of having a Deſign upon the City of <hi>London</hi> for the Firing of it: I ſo much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the Thought of the Thing that ſhould have been done, as they ſay, for the carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on of ſuch a Deſign, (if my Heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive me not) had I known it, I ſo much ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor the Thing, I ſhould have been the firſt diſcoverer of it: Nor ever had I Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency or Meetings with ſuch Perſons as would have carried on ſuch a Deſign. It is ſaid likewiſe, I entertained the Earl, the Marqueſs of <hi>Ormond;</hi> to my Remembrance I never ſaw the Face of that Honourable Perſon in my Life. It is ſaid, One Lords Day I did preach at Saint <hi>Gregory</hi>'s and the next Lords Day I was at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> or <hi>Bruges,</hi> and kiſt the Kings Hand, and brought I cannot tell what Orders and Inſtructions from him; this I ſhall ſay, For theſe three Years laſt paſt together, I have not been ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Miles from this City of <hi>London,</hi> and I
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54496:44"/>think it is ſomewhat further to either of thoſe Places then threeſcore Miles. It is ſaid that I kept Correſpondence with one <hi>Barrow</hi> and <hi>Biſhop;</hi> they are Perſons I have heard of their Names, but never ſaw their Faces, and to my Knowledge I do not know they knew me; nor do I know them at all, but only as I have heard of their Names. And whoſoever elſe hath ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch things againſt me, I know not.</p>
            <p>His Highneſs was pleaſed to tell me, I was like a flaming Torch in the midſt of a Sheaf of Corn; he meaning, I being a publick Preacher, was able to ſet the City on Fire by Sedition and Combuſtions, and promoting D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſigns. Here truly I do ſay, and have it from many of thoſe that are Judges of the High Court, that upon Examination of the Buſineſs they have not found me a Meddler at all in theſe Affairs. And truly, I muſt needs ſay therefore, that it was a very uncharitable Act in them (who ever they were) that brought ſuch Accuſations againſt me, and irritated his Highneſs againſt me, I will not ſay it was Malice, it might be Zeal, but it was raſh zeal which cauſed me to be ſentenced to this Place; the God of Mercy pardon and forgive them all, and truly as I am a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church, and as a Member of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:54496:45"/>the Community whereon behalf I have been ſpeaking, I cannot but do as our Saviour himſelf did for his Diſciples when he was to be taken from them, he bleſſed them, and aſcended up to Heaven. My Truſt is in the Mercy of the moſt High, I ſhall not miſcarry; and however my Days are ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by this unexpected doom, and ſhall be brought untimely to the Grave: I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not go without my Prayers for a Bleſſing upon all the People of this Land, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but bleſs them all in the Name of God, and beſeech God to bleſs them in all their Ways, and his Bleſſing be upon them.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="prayer">
               <body>
                  <head>Let us Pray.</head>
                  <p>O Moſt glorious Lord God, thou whoſe Dwelling is ſo far above the Higheſt Heavens, that thou humbleſt thy ſelf but to look upon the Things that are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and that are in Earth, and thou doeſt whatſoever thou wilt both in Heaven, in Earth, in the Sea, and in all deep Places; in thy Hands are the Hearts of all Men, and thou turneſt them which way ſoever thou wilt, O Lord look in Mercy and Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we beſeech thee, on this great and innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous People of this Land; look upon them O Lord, withan Eye of Pity, not with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Eye of Fury and Indignation; O look
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54496:45"/>not upon all thoſe great and grievous Sins that have provoked thee moſt juſtly to Wrath and Diſpleaſure againſt us. Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God, who can ſtand in thy Sight when thou art angry? When thou with rebuke doſt correct Man for Sin, thou makeſt his Beauty to conſume away like as it were a Moth fretting a Garment. O Lord, thy Indignation and Wrath lies heavy upon us, and thou haſt vexed us with thy Scourges, thou haſt made us a Reproach and a by Word amongſt our Neighbours, and the very Heathens laugh us to ſcorn. O that thou wouldſt turn us again, O Lord God of Hoſts; that thou wouldſt ſhew us the Light of thy Countenance, that we may behold it; that thou wouldſt humble us for all thoſe Sins and grievous Tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons that are amongſt us; for thoſe Atheiſms, for thoſe Infidelities, horrid Blaſphemies, and Prophaneneſs; for thoſe Sacriledges, for thoſe Hereſies, for thoſe Schiſms, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and all thoſe Blindneſſes of Heart, Pride, vain Glory, and Hypocriſie; for that Envy, Hatred, and Malice, and all Uncharitableneſs, that hath ſet us one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, that we are ſo daſhed one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, even to deſtroy each other; <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> and <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Ephraim,</hi> and both againſt <hi>Judah.</hi> O
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:54496:46"/>Lord we are like thoſe Moabites and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monites, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — This thou haſt done to us O Lord, becauſe we have rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee: O how greatly and grievouſly have we ſinned againſt thee, yet for all this, thou haſt not requited us according to our ill deſervings, for thou mighteſt have brought us to Deſolation and Deſtruction; Fire might have come down from Heaven, and deſtroyed us; our Foreign Enemies, and the Enemies of thee, and thy Chriſt our Saviour, might have ſwallowed us up. What have we not deſerved! yet O the long Suffering, and Patience, and Goodneſs of our God! O Lord our God, we pray thee that thy Patience and long Suffering might lead to Repentance that thou wouldſt be pleaſed, thou who delighteſt not in the Death of a Sinner, but rather that he ſhould turn from his Sins and live, that thou wouldſt turn us unto thee O Lord, and we ſhall be turned; draw us, and we ſhall run after thee; draw us with the Cords of Love, and by the Bands of loving kindneſs, by the powerful working of thy Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in our Souls, working Contrition in our Hearts, and a Godly Sorrow for all our Sins, even a Sorrow to Repentance, and a Repentance to Salvation never to be repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of. Lord break thoſe ſtnoy Hearts of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:54496:46"/>ours by the Hammer of thy Word, mollify them by the Oil of thy Grace, ſmite theſe rocky Hearts of ours by the Rod of thy moſt gracious Power, that we may ſhed forth Rivers of Tears for all the Sins we have committed. O that thou wouldſt make us grieve becauſe we cannot grieve, and to weep becauſe we cannot weep enough; that thou wouldſt humble us more and more in the true Sight and Senſe of all our Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation againſt thee; and that thou wouldſt be pleaſed in the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt to cleanſe us from all our Sins; Lord let his Blood that ſpeaks better Things than that of <hi>Abel,</hi> cry louder in thine Ears, for Mercy, then all thoſe Miſchiefs and Wickedneſſes that have been done amongſt us for Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance. O beſprinkle our polluted, but Penitent Souls, in the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, that we may be clean in thy Sight, and that the Light of thy Countenance may ſhine upon us. Lord be pleaſed to Seal unto our Souls the free Pardon and Forgiveneſs of all our Sins; ſay to each of our Souls, and ſay that we may hear it, that thou art well pleaſed with us, and appeaſed towards us. Lord, do thou by the Spirit aſſure our Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, that we are thy Children, and that thou art reconciled to us in the Blood of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> To this end, O Lord, create in us
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:54496:47"/>new Hearts, and renew right Spirits within us. Caſt us not away from thy Preſence, and take not thy Holy Spirit from us; but give us the Comfort of thy Help, and eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh us with thy free Spirit. Help us to live as thy redeemed ones; and (Lord) let us not any longer by our wicked Lives deny that moſt Holy Faith whereof our Lips have for ſo long Time made Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but let us that call on the Name of the Lord Jeſus, depart from Iniquity, and hate every evil Way. Help us to caſt away all our Tranſgreſſions, whereby we have tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, and make us new Hearts. Carry us along through the Pilgrimage of this World, ſupplying us with all Things need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for us; thy Grace alone is ſufficient for us: Lord, let thy Grace be aſſiſtant to us to ſtrengthen us againſt all the Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Satan, eſpecially againſt thoſe Sins whereunto we are moſt prone, either by Cuſtom or Conſtitution, or moſt eaſily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked. O Lord, with what Affliction ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever thou ſhalt puniſh us, do not puniſh us with ſpiritual Judgments and Deſertions. Give us not over to our own Hearts Luſts to our vile, lewd, and corrupt Affections; give us not over to Hardneſs and Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency of Heart, but make us ſenſible of the leaſt Sin, and give us thy Grace to think no
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:54496:47"/>Sin little committed againſt thee our God, but that we may be humbled for it, and repent of it, and reform it in our Dives and Converſations; and Lord keep us from Preſumptuous Sins, O let not them get the Dominion over us, but keep us Innocent from the great Offence, O Lord our Strength and our Redeemer. And Lord ſanctify unto us all thy Methods and Proceedings with us, fitting us for all further Tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Tryals whatſoever thou in thy divine Pleaſure ſhalt be pleaſed to impoſe upon us; Lord give us Patience, Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, Reſolution and Fortitude to undergo them, that though we walk through the Valley of the Shadow of Death, we may fear none ill; knowing that thou O Lord, art mercifully with us, and that with thy Rod as well as with thy Staff thou wilt ſupport and comfort us; and that nothing ſhall be able to ſeperate us from thy Love which is in Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                  <p>And (gracious God) we beſeech thee be thou pleaſed to look mercifully and compaſſionately on thy Holy Catholick Church, and grant that all they that do confeſs thy Holy Name, may agree together in the Truth of thy Holy Word, and live in Unity and godly Love. Thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed O Lord, the Gates of Hell ſhall not
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:54496:48"/>prevail againſt thy Church; perform we beſeech thee, thy moſt gracious promiſes both to thy whole Church, and to that Part of it which thou haſt planted, and now afflicted in theſe ſinful Lands and Nations wherein we live; ariſe, O Lord, and have Mercy upon our <hi>Sion,</hi> for it is time that thou have Mercy upon her, yea, the Time is come, for thy Servants think upon her Stones, and it pittieth them to ſee her in the Duſt. Lord maintain thine own Cauſe, reſcue the Light of thy Truth from all thoſe Clouds of Errors and Hereſies, which do ſo much obſcure it, and let the Light thereof in a free Proffeſſion break forth and ſhine again among us, and that continually, even as long as the Sun and Moon endures.</p>
                  <p>To this end, O Lord bleſs us all, and bleſs him, the Poſterity — which in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ought to rule over, and be above us; Bleſs him in his Soul, and in his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in his Friends, and in his Servants, and all his Relations: Guide him by thy Council, proſper him in all Undertakings, granting him a long, proſperous, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Life here upon Earth, and that he may attain to a Bleſſed Life hereafter. And gracious God, look mercifully upon all our Relations, and do thou bring them to the Light of thy Truth that are wander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:54496:48"/>and ready to fall. Confirm them in thy Truth that already ſtand, ſhow ſome good Token for good unto them, that they may rejoyce. O let thy good Hand of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence be over them in all their Ways. And to all Orders and Degrees of Men that be amongſt us, give Religious Hearts to them that now rule in Authority over us: Loyal Hearts in the Subjects towards their Supream, and loving Hearts in all Men to their Friends, and charitable Hearts one towards another. And for the Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of thy Goſpel among us, reſtore in thy good Time to their ſeveral Places and Callings, and give Grace O Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to all Biſhops, Paſtors, and Curates, that they may both by their Life and Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ſet forth thy true and lively Word, and rightly and duly adminiſter thy Holy Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. And Lord bleſs thy Church ſtill with Paſtors after thine own Heart, with a continual Succeſſion of faithful and able Men, that they may both by Life and Doctrine declare thy Truth, and never for fear or favour backſlide or depart from the ſame; and give them the Aſſiſtance of thy Spirit that may enable them ſo to preach thy Word, that may keep the People up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right in the midſt of a corrupted and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Generation. And good Lord bleſs thy
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:54496:49"/>People every where with hearing Ears, underſtanding Hearts, conſcientious Souls, and obedient Lives, eſpecially thoſe over whom I have had either lately or formerly a charge, that with meek Heart and due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence they may hear and receive thy Holy Word, truly ſerving thee in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs all the Days of their Lives.</p>
                  <p>And we beſeech the of thy Goodneſs and Mercy to comfort and ſuccour all thoſe that in this tranſitory Life be in Trouble, Sorrow, Need, Sickneſs or any other Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; Lord help the Helpleſs, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the Comfortleſs, vifit the Sick, relieve the Oppreſſed, help them to right that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer wrong, ſet them at Liberty that are in Priſon, reſtore the Baniſhed, and of thy great Mercy, and in thy good Time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver all thy People out of their Neceſſities: Lord do thou of thy great Mercy fit us all for our latter end, for the Hour of Death and the Day of Judgment; and do thou in the Hour of Death and at the Day of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from thy Wrath and everlaſting Damnation, good Lord deliver us, through the Croſs and Paſſion of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>In the mean Time, O Lord teach us ſo to number our Days, and me my Minutes, that we may apply our Hearts to true
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:54496:49"/>Wiſdom; that we may be Wiſe unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that we may live ſoberly, Godly, and Righteouſly in this preſent World, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts: Lords teach us ſo to live, that we may not be afraid to dye, and that we may ſo live that we may be always prepared to dye that when Death ſhall ſeize upon us it may not ſurprize us, but that we may lift up our Heads with Joy, knowing that our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption draws nigh, and that we ſhall be for ever happy, being aſſured that we ſhall come to the Felicity of the Choſen, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice with the Gladneſs of the People; and give us ſuch a fullneſs of thy Holy Spirit that may make us ſtedfaſt in this Faith, and confirm us in this Hope; indue us with Patience under thy afflicting Hand, and withal a chearful Reſolution of our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves to thy divine diſpoſing; that ſo paſſing the Pilgrimage of this World, we may come to the Land of Promiſe the Heavenly <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> that we may reign with thee in the World to come, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; in whoſe bleſſed Name and Words we farther call upon thee, ſaying, Our Father <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let thy mighty Hand, and out-ſtretched Arm, O Lord, be the Defence of me and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:54496:50"/>all other thy ſervants, thy mercy and lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kindneſs in Jeſus Chriſt our ſalvation, thy true and holy word our inſtruction, thy grace and holy Spirit our comfort and conſolation, to the end, and in the end, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Amen,</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>His Speech and Prayer ended with much Meekneſs and ſpiritual Conſolation. He ſubmitted his Neck to the ſtroak of the Ax, to as great a Loſs of the Church of Chriſt, and of all good Men, as hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in our Times. I have the more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged my ſelf, that my Reader might not without a kind of a Conſternation or Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of ſtrange Amazement paſs by the Concernments of this bleſſed Heroe.</p>
            <p>The ſame Day of Doctor <hi>Hewets</hi> Tryal, was alſo tryed <hi>John Mordant</hi> of <hi>Clement Danes</hi> Eſquire, with whom he was a Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Priſoner; the Charge againſt him, was for combining with <hi>Henry Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Parham</hi> in <hi>Suſſex</hi> Gent. <hi>Hartgil Baron,</hi> and <hi>Francis Manſil,</hi> with divers others for raiſing War againſt <hi>Oliver</hi> Lord Protector, in the behalf of <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> and confering with <hi>J. Stapely,</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> 
               <hi>Henry Mallory,</hi> and others, how to effect the ſame; and delivering Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions to ſeveral Perſons in the Name of, and as from the ſaid <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:54496:50"/>He ſtood long upon it (as did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Doctor before) to have Council aſſigne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, and that he might be tryed by a Jury; but finding it would not be granted, he at laſt pleaded not Guilty, many Witneſſes depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited againſt him; yet he by his Ingenuity ſo cleared himſelf; that notwithſtanding many Endeavours to the contrary, he was diſcharged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>July</hi> the 17. following, Colonel <hi>Aſhton</hi> and <hi>John Betley</hi> were executed, the one in <hi>Tower-ſtreet,</hi> the other in <hi>Cheap-ſide:</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel <hi>Aſhton</hi> was the firſt, being drawn on a Sledge, that Worthy Divine Doctor <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtry</hi> ſubmitting for the good of a poor Chriſtians Soul to lie along with him upon the Sledge, that he might loſe no Time for his ſpiritual Converſe. They were drawn from <hi>Newgate</hi> to <hi>Tower-ſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Mark-lane</hi> end, where a Gibbet was erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. As he aſcended the Ladder, Doctor <hi>Warmeſtry</hi> ſaid, <hi>Almighty God, who is a ſtrong Tower, be with thee, and make thee know and feel, that there is no other Name under Heaven, whereby to attain everlaſting Life, but by the Name of Jeſus. The Bleſſing of God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Son, and Holy Ghoſt be with you hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth and for ever,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>He being upon the <hi>Ladder,</hi> expreſt a great deal of Confidence he had in the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:54496:51"/>Merits and Mercies of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; not doubting but that through the red Sea of his Blood he ſhould arrive at the Heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and in little ſpace behold his Saviour, whom his Soul ſo much longed after. Then fixing his Eyes upon the Multitude, he ſpake to this effect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am brought here to a ſhameful Death; I am an Engliſh Man born, and (as many know) a Gentleman born; I was drawn into this Buſineſs by ſeveral Perſons, and am now brought here for my former Sins: God hath delivered me ſeveral Times from ſeveral Judgments, he hath viſited me at this Time; becauſe I ſlighted and did not purſue that Repentance that I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. Therefore I deſire all good People to leave off their Sins for Chriſt his ſake, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agme new Men, for it is that that brings all Men to ruin: I beſeech God of Mercy have Mercy upon my Soul, Lord God I come to thee, Lord the Father of Heaven have Mercy upon me O God the Son Redeemer of the World have Mercy upon me, O God the Holy Ghoſt proceeding from the Father and the Son have Mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y upon me. Remember not my Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, but ſpare me, good Lord God; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee ſpare thy Servant whom thou haſt vedeamed, for thy dear Sons ſake. I have no more to ſay, but deſire the Prayers of all good People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:54496:51"/>
Having ended his Speech he committed his Spirit into the Hands of God, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaid, <hi>Lord have Morcy upon my Soul,</hi> he was turned off the Ladder, and inſtantly cut down, his Belly ripped up, and his Bowels burnt in a Fire ready prepared for that purpoſe; he being not yet Dead; then was his Head cut off, and his Body divided into four Quarters, put into a Basket and conveyed back to <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next they proceeded and fetcht <hi>John Betley</hi> (for there was a great deal of Buſineſs done by the Executioner that Day) into <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> where formerly the Croſs ſtood; where was likewiſe a Gibbet ſet up; being come to the Place with a Miniſter, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter read, and the People ſung with him a Pſalm, beginning thus, <hi>O Lord conſider my Diſtreſs,</hi> &amp;c. Then he went up the Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſaid as followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LOrd receive my Soul, and be merciful to me; I commit my Soul into Almighty Gods Hands; for he is my Protector and Redeemer. I am not aſhamed to live, nor afraid to die; for my Converſation hath been ſuch, in Chriſt Jeſus I hope I ſhall find Mercy. As concerning them that are my Enemies, I pray God forgive them their Sins, I freely forgive them all that have done me wrong. As for the late Plot, I
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:54496:52"/>was never but once in Company with them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned therein: I did know of ſuch a Thing, but deny that I acted therein. Shall I damn my Soul at this Inſtant? I will ſpeak the Truth. One</hi> Brandon, <hi>that was one of them, drew me into the Buſineſs, and his Man. I carrying Work to him, could not refrain his Houſe, he ſo often enticed me thereto, and would not let me alone, till he had got me into a Houſe, where we drank together. I have no more to ſay as to the Plot, but deſire Mercy from God.</hi> Having this ſaid, the Executioner turned him off, and the reſt of the Sentence was executed upon him, as before upon Colonel <hi>Aſhton,</hi> and his Head and Quarters were conveyed alſo to <hi>Newgate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some two Days after, one <hi>Edmund Stacy</hi> alſo about the ſame Conſpiracy was execut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Cornhil</hi> over againſt the <hi>Exchange;</hi> as alſo a Youth in <hi>Smithfield</hi> having the Rope about his Neck, the horror of Death being worſe then Death it ſelf, but for his Souls Health, was Reprieved, the Torrent of Blood being for a while ſtayed.</p>
            <p>Whilſt theſe Tradgedies were acting on the Land, a ſtrange Accident no leſs prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious happened on the Water; a Whale of a monſtrous bigneſs, at leaſt ſixty Foot, and of a proportionable Breadth, was caſt up
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:54496:52"/>on the River of <hi>Thames</hi> near <hi>London;</hi> which by the common People was accounted a Prognoſtication of the Protectors Death, which enſued not long after.</p>
            <p>But to return to <hi>Flanders,</hi> where we for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly left, the Sea whereof like a ſharp Humour did always nouriſh the Wounds of incurable Evils; nor was the <hi>French</hi> their letting of her Blood ſufficient, ſhe wanted an Engliſh Phyſician to treat her. Our Armies, whoſe Valours made not a ſtand at <hi>Mardike,</hi> but with a gallant Reſolution beſieged <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> which being a Place of great Importance, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> intended to relieve; and with an Army of ſixteen thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, came within an Engliſh Mile and a half of the French Quarters; whereupon the <hi>Engeiſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> uniting their Forces, leaving ſome part of them before <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> to make good the Approaches, and guard the Trenches; with fifteen thouſand Men, and ten Pieces of Cannon, ſet upon the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> whom after a long and ſharp Fight, they put to a total Rout and Confuſion, with the Loſs of three thouſand five hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men; which Victory was in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wholy attributed to the Valour of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi> The Loſs of this Day loſt the Spaniard <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> who quickly after ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendered up the Town upon theſe following Conditions.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:54496:53"/>
1. <hi>That the Town ſhall be yielded up, with all their great Guns, their ſtores of Victuals, Magazines of Arms, and Ammunition, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any embezlement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That all Officers and Soldiers ſhall have Liberty to marth out with their Arms, Drums beating, Golours flying, two Pieces of Oridinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, and their Baggage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That they ſhall have the Liberty to march with a Convoy ſo conduct them to Saint</hi> Omers.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That the Inhabitants ſhould remain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempnified in their Perſons and Goods, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying their former Cuſtoms and Priviledges for two Years, and not be moleſted touching the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Articles ſigned, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, being about one Thouſand Horſe and Foot, and ſeven hundred more that were wounded; the <hi>French</hi> (according as it was articled before) put the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion thereof, which ever ſince they have maintained.</p>
            <p>I have heard of an expreſſion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of <hi>Oſtend.</hi> A little before the Maſſacre there, a Perſon of Quality being ſent thither about the exchange of Priſoners, after he was civilly treated, the Glaſſes of Wine going freely about; the Governour being in a ſafe Place began to throw forth Words to this effect; <hi>Sir, is this the Mode of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:54496:53"/>your Muſhroom Protector, hath he no other Way to pay my Maſter the King of</hi> Spain <hi>for his Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, but with Bullets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after the taking of <hi>Dunkirk</hi> deceaſed the Lady <hi>Cleypoll,</hi> ſecond Daughter to the Protector; a Lady whom Poſterity will mention with an honourable Character, who often interpoſed, and became an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Supplicant to her Father for many Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons deſign'd to dye; her laſt requeſt as it was thought, for ſome eminent Perſons be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deny'd, was a means of haſtening her Death, which much ſadned her Father's Spirits; nor did he long ſurvive her, her Death cauſing more Wounds in his Heart, than all he received in the Wars.</p>
            <p>But as his Severity was great to his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, ſo did he excell in Gratitude to his Friends; amongſt other Examples, I ſhall Inſtance in the Perſon of one <hi>Duret</hi> a French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who attonded him during his Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralſhip, and ſerved him with ſo much Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Zeal, as that he entruſted him with the Managing and Conduct of the greateſt Part of his Domeſtick Affairs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways retaining him nigh his Perſon, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo great an affection towards him, and repoſing ſo entire a Confidence in him, that during a great Sickneſs which he had in <hi>Scotland,</hi> (and whereof it was thought he
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:54496:54"/>wou'd have died) he would not be ſerved by any one, nor receive any nouriſhment, or any thing elſe that was adminiſter'd unto him, ſave from the Hands of <hi>Duret,</hi> who both Day and Night continued to watch by his Maſter; tending him with a ſpecial care and aſſiduity, not giving himſelf a Moments reſt until his Maſter had recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his perfect Health; which long and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Watches of <hi>Duret,</hi> and the great Pains he had taken, drove him into a ſad fit of Sickneſs; to recover him, his endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Maſter in retribution of his great Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſpared no Coſt, but applied all poſſible means that could be procured, not only by his Commands, but by his perſonal Viſits (ſo oft as his urgent Affairs would permit.) <hi>Duret</hi> dying, he ſends over into <hi>France</hi> for his Mother, Siſter and two Nephews, to requite in them the Obligations he owed to his deceaſed Friend and Servant; and where as by reaſon of the continuance of the Scotch Wars, he was as it were confin'd to the North, he wrote unto his Wife, <q>That ſhe ſhould proportion that Kindneſs which during his Abſence ſhe ſhould ſhew unto them, to the Love which ſhe bare unto him.</q> In ſomuch that <hi>Duret</hi>'s Mother was admitted into her own Family, and ſeated at her own Table; his Siſter was placed in
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:54496:54"/>the rank and Quality of a Maid of Honour, and his two Nephews were admitted to be her Highneſſes Pages, which Love of his he extended towards them to the Day of his Death.</p>
            <p>One writes, that when he came to have more abſolute Power towards the latter End of his Days, that he hath been heard often to wiſh, that thoſe that had been put to Death were yet alive; proteſting ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly, that if he could not have changed their Hearts, he would have changed their Dooms, and converted their Deaths into Baniſhment.</p>
            <p>Waving this digreſſion, as in reſpect of the diſtance of Time, we are now come to his own approaching Cataſtrope. His Death was uſhered in by an extraordinary Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, and violent guſt of Weather, which blew down ſome Houſes, tore up the Trees by the Roots, one in the old <hi>Palace Yar'd</hi> by the Parliament-Houſe, which by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent hath ſignified no otherwiſe then the Root and Branch of his Government. It was a horrid Tempeſt, as if Nature would have the Protectors Death to be accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a general horrour. The ſame is elegantly ſet forth in a Poem by the ſame Laureat. I ſhall ſet down his ſmooth Poem, which was anſwered as roughly in reſpect
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:54496:55"/>of the ſingle rapier'd Senſe, though other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in the ſame <hi>Virgil</hi> ſtile, Line for Line; the latter as too Satyrical I have ommitted, the other follows.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>We muſt reſign, Heaven his great Soul doth claim</l>
               <l>In Storms as loud as his immortal Fame.</l>
               <l>His dying Groans, his laſt Breath ſhakes our Iſle,</l>
               <l>And Trees uncut fall for his Funeral Pile;</l>
               <l>About his Palace their broad Roots were toſt,</l>
               <l>Into the Air, ſo <hi>Romulus</hi> was loſt:</l>
               <l>New <hi>Rome</hi> in ſuch a Tempeſt miſt their King,</l>
               <l>And from Obeying fell to Worſhipping,</l>
               <l>On <hi>Aetna's</hi> top, thus <hi>Hercules</hi> lay dead,</l>
               <l>With ruin'd Oaks, and Pines about him ſpread,</l>
               <l>Thoſe his laſt Fury from the Mountain rent,</l>
               <l>Our dying <hi>Hero</hi> from the continent.</l>
               <l>Raviſh't whole Towns, and Forts from Spaniards reft,</l>
               <l>As his Laſt Legacy to <hi>Brittain</hi> left.</l>
               <l>The Ocean which ſo long our Hopes confin'd,</l>
               <l>Could give no Limits to his vaſter Mind:</l>
               <l>Our Bounds enlargement was his lateſt Toil,</l>
               <l>Nor hath he left us Priſoners to our Iſle,</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder the Tropick is our Language ſpoke,</l>
               <l>And part of <hi>Flanders</hi> hath receiv'd our yoke.</l>
               <l>From Civil Broyles he did us diſengage,</l>
               <l>Found nobler Objects for our Martial rage;</l>
               <l>And with wiſe Conduct to his Country ſhow'd</l>
               <l>Their ancient way of conquering abroad.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngrestful then it were no Tears t' allow</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:54496:55"/>
To him that gave us Peace and Empire too:</l>
               <l>Princes that fear'd him grieve, concern'd, to ſee</l>
               <l>No pitch of Glory from the Grave is free.</l>
               <l>Nature her ſelf took notice of his Death,</l>
               <l>And ſighing ſwell'd the Sea with ſuch a Breath;</l>
               <l>That to remoteſt ſhores her Billows roll'd,</l>
               <l>The approaching Fate of their great Ruler told.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>September</hi> the third, 1658, he march'd off from his earthly Honours, and received his Writ of Eaſe from all his Labours, as Death alone was able to encounter him, which was on a Day, one Year after another, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1650, and <hi>Anno</hi> 1651, rubrickt with two of his remarkable Victories; as <hi>Antipater</hi> died the ſame Day of his riſing. But as concerning the manner of his Death, after he had been ſick about a Fortnight of the Diſeaſe, which at the beginning was but an Ague, of which <hi>Tamberlain</hi> died; on <hi>Friday</hi> being the third of <hi>September</hi> 1658. in the Morning he gave all the Signs of a dying Perſon; he remained in that manner till three of the Clock in the Afternoon; he had to his laſt a perfect and intire Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, his greateſt and moſt important Affair was to name a Protector to be his Succeſſor, which after his deceaſe was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentaneouſly confirmed on his eldeſt Son <hi>Richard;</hi> he died in the midſt of his Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:54496:56"/>and Triumphs, and in a Bed of Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers. On his Death-bed he diſpatcht ſeveral Buſineſſes of Conſequence, anſwering the Phyſicians who reproved him, as the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror did, <hi>That a Governour ought to die ſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great was born on the ſixth Day of <hi>April,</hi> on the like Day the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> at <hi>Epheſus</hi> was burnt preſaging that Fire which this Conqueror ſhould kindle in <hi>Aſia.</hi> The ſame <hi>Gnatho,</hi> from whom I borrow this example, who hath many more, but at laſt, ſaith he, to look no further then our own Country, into our own Hiſtories, it is obſerved that the late <hi>Richard</hi> the ſucceeding Protector was inſtalled in his Protectorſhip the third Day of <hi>September,</hi> when as <hi>Richard</hi> the Firſt ſo much ſpoken of in our Hiſtories, begun his Reign; an Accident, ſaith he, which cannot but promiſe him a moſt favourable Om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, and good Token: But a blunt Fellow in two ruſtical Verſes hath ſince, as to the event, better ſpecified.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>That his ſucceſſors Government ne'er ſtaid,</l>
               <l>A ſtray'd Sheeps Time, not to be year'd and dayd.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>As to the remarkable Paſſages which happened on the like Days of <hi>Olivers</hi> Life,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:54496:56"/>ſome have obſerved, that on the third of <hi>September</hi> he was confirmed in his Protector<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip by the Parliament; on the third of <hi>September</hi> he gained that Battle of <hi>Dunbar;</hi> on the third of <hi>September</hi> he gained that great Battle of <hi>Worceſter;</hi> and on the third of <hi>September</hi> he died at <hi>White Hall;</hi> with all the Comforts that good Hopes could give in his Poſterity.</p>
            <p>His Corps being embalmed, and wrapped up in a Sheet of Lead, were <hi>September</hi> the 26, about ten of the Clock at Night, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately removed from <hi>White Hall</hi> to <hi>Somerſet Houſe,</hi> where it remained till the 23 of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> lying in the mean Time in ſo great State, as would puzzle Antiquity to ſhew ſuch a Preſident; which by ſome was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted an unneceſſary Vanity, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth at that Tim being ſo involved in Debts both to the Soldiery, the Navy, and others.</p>
            <p>The three firſt Rooms at <hi>Somerſet-Houſe</hi> where the Spectators entered, were hung with black, having in each of them a Cloth of State, with a Chair of State under the ſame, at the Head of each Cloth of State was fixed a large Majeſtick Scutcheon fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly painted and gilt upon Taſſaty, and all the Rooms furniſhed with Scutcheons of his Arms, crowned with the Imperial Crown</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:54496:57"/>
The fourth Room where both the Corps and the Effigies did lye, was compleatly hung with black Velvet, the Roof ceiled with Velvet, and a large Canopy or Cloth of State of black Velvet ſringed, was plated over the Effigies made to the Life in Wax. The Effigies it ſelf being apparel'd in a rich ſuit of uncut Velvet, robed in a little Robe of Purple Velvet, laced with a rich geld Face, and furr'd with Ermins; upon the Kirtle was the Royal large Robe of the like Purple Velvet, laced and furred with Ermins; with rich ſtrings and taſſels of Gold: the Kirtle being girt with a rich embroidered Belt, wherein was a fair Sword richly gilt and hatch'd with Gold, hanging by the ſide of the Eſſigies. In the Right Fland was the Golden Scepter, repreſenting Government; in the Left Hand the Globe, denoting Principality; upon the Head a Purple Velvet Cap furr'd with Ermins, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying Regality: Behind the Head there was placed a Rich Chair of State of tiſſued Gold, and upon the Cuſhion which lay thereon was placed an Imperial Crown ſet with precious Stones. The Body of the Effigies lay upon a Bed of ſtate covered with a large Pall of black Velvet, under which there was ſpread a fine Holland Sheet upon ſix Stools of tiſſued Cloth of Gold: on the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:54496:57"/>ſides of the Bed of State was placed a rich ſuit of Compleat Armour, and at the Feet thereof ſtood his Creſt.</p>
            <p>The Bed of State whereupon the Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies did thus lye, was aſcended unto by two Steps covered with the aforeſaid Pall of Velvet; at each corner whereof there was placed an upright Pillar covered with Velvet, upon the Tops whereof were the four Supporters of the Imperial Arms, bearing Banners or Streamers crowned. The Pillars were adorned with Trophies of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Honour, carved and gilt, the Pedeſtals of the Pillars had Shields and Crowns gilt, which compleated the whole Work, cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Velvet: within the Rails ſtood eight ſilver Candleſticks, or Standards, almoſt five foot high, with Virgin-wax Tapers of a yard long; next unto the Candleſticks there were ſet upright in Sockets the four great Standards of his Arms, the Guydons, great Banners, and Banrolls of War, being all of Taffety very richly gilt and painted. The Cloth of State which covered the Bed and the Effigies, had a Majeſtick Scutcheon; and the whole Room adorned with Taffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Scutcheons, ſeveral of his Servants at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending bare-headed, to ſet out the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony with the greater Luſtre.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:54496:58"/>
After this (to ſhew there is no intermiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Vanity) his Effigies was ſeveral Days ſhown in another Room, ſtanding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an aſcent under a rich Cloth of State; veſted in Royal Robes, having a Scepter in one Hand, and a Globe in the other, a Crown on his Head, his Armour lying by him at a diſtance, and the Banners, Banrolls, and Standards being placed round about him, together with the other Enſigns of Honour, the whole Room being adorned in a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtical manner, and his Servants ſtanding by bare-headed, as before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>November</hi> the 23. was the Day appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Solemnization of the Funerals, multitudes were the Spectators, which from all Places came to behold it, ſo much are we taken with Novelty, that we think no coſt too much for the beholding a two or three Hours Vanity. The Effigies being a while placed in the middle of a Room, was carried on the Hearſe by ten Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men into the Court-yard, where a very rich Canopy of State was born over it by ſix o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemen, till it was brought and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in a Chariot; at each end whereof was a ſeat wherein ſat two of his late Highneſs Gentlemen of the Bed-Chamber; the Pall which was made of Velvet, and the White Linnen was very large, extending on each
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:54496:58"/>ſide of the Carriage and was born up by ſeveral Perſons of Honour. The Chariot wherein the Effigies was conveyed, was co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with black Velvet, adorned with Plumes and Scutcheons, and was drawn by ſix Horſes covered with black Velvet, and each of them adorned with Plumes of black Feathers.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Somerſet-Houſe</hi> to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Streets were railed in, and ſtrewed with Sand; the Soldiers being placed on each ſide of the Streets without the Rails, and their Enſigns wrapped up in a Cypreſs mourning Veil.</p>
            <p>The manner of the proceeding to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terment was briefly thus. Firſt, a Knight Martial advanced on Horſe-back with his black Truncheon tipt at both ends with Gold, attended by his Deputy and thirteen Men on Horſe-back to clear the Way.</p>
            <p>After him followed the poor Men of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in mourning Gowns and Hoods, marching two and two.</p>
            <p>Next unto them followed the Servants of the ſeveral Perſons of all Qualities, which attended the Funeral.</p>
            <p>Theſe were followed by all his own Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, as well inferiour as ſuperiour, both within and without the Houſhold, as alſo all his Bargemen at Watermen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:54496:59"/>
Next unto theſe followed the Servants and Officers belonging to the Lord Mayor, and Sheriffs of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then came ſeveral Gentlemen and Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants on the reſpective Ambaſſadors, and the other publick Miniſters.</p>
            <p>After theſe came the poor Knights of <hi>Windſor</hi> in Gowns and Hoods.</p>
            <p>Then followed the Clerks, Secretaries, and other Officers belonging to the Army, the Admiralty, the Treaſury, the Navy, and Exchequer.</p>
            <p>After theſe came the Officers in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in the Fleet, as alſo the Officers of the Army.</p>
            <p>Next followed the Commiſſioners for Exciſe, thoſe of the Army, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the Navy.</p>
            <p>Then followed the Commiſſioners for the Approbation of Preachers.</p>
            <p>Then came the Officers, Meſſengers, and Clerks belonging to the Privy Council, and the Clerks of both Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>Next followed his late Highneſs Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians.</p>
            <p>The Head Officers of the Army.</p>
            <p>The chief Officers and Aldermen of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Maſters of the Chancery, with his Highneſs learned Council at Law.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:54496:59"/>
The Judges of the Admiralty, the Maſters of Requeſt, with the Judges in <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Barrons of the Exchequer, the Jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of both Benches, and the Lord Mayor of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next to theſe the Perſons allied in Blood to the late Protector, and the Members of the Lords Houſe.</p>
            <p>After them the publick Miniſters of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign States and Princes.</p>
            <p>Then the Holland Ambaſſador alone, whoſe Train was born up by four Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <p>Next to him the Portugal Ambaſſador alone, whoſe Train was held up by four Knights of the Order of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And thirdly the French Ambaſſador, whoſe Train was alſo held up by four Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality.</p>
            <p>Then followed the Lords Commiſſioners of the great Seal.</p>
            <p>The Lords Commiſſioners of the Treaſury.</p>
            <p>The Lords of the late Protectors Privy Council.</p>
            <p>After whom followed the Chief Mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and thoſe Perſons of Quality which were his Aſſiſtants, and bare up his Train. All the Nobles were in cloſe Mourning, the reſt were but in ordinary, being diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:54496:60"/>in their Paſſage into ſeveral di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſions, being diſtinguiſhed by Drums and Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and by a Standard or Banner born by a Perſon of Honour, and his Aſſiſtant, and a Horſe of State covered with black Velvet, and led by a Perſon of Honour, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by two Grooms: Of which Horſes there were eleven in all, four covered with black Cloth, and ſeven with Velvet. Theſe being all paſſed in Order, at length the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot followed with the Effigies, on each ſide of which were born ſix Banner Rolls, twelve in all, by as many Perſons of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. The ſeveral Pieces of his Armour were born by eight Officers of the Army, attended by a Herald and a Gentleman on each ſide. Next followed <hi>Gartar</hi> principal King of Arms, attended with a Gentleman on each ſide bare-headed.</p>
            <p>Then came the chief Mourner, together with thoſe Lords and other Perſonages that were Supporters and Aſſiſtants to the chief Mourner.</p>
            <p>Then followed the Horſe of Honour in very rich Trappings embroidered upon Crimſon Velvet, and adorned with White, Red, and Yellow Plumes, and was led by the Maſter of the Horſe.</p>
            <p>Finally, in the cloſe of all followed thoſe of his late Guard, and the Warders of the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:54496:60"/>
At the Weſt Gate of the Abbey Church in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the Hearſe with the Effigies thereon was taken off again from the Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ot by thoſe ten Gentlemen who placed it thereon before, and in their paſſing on to carry it into the Church, the Canopy of State was by the former ſix Gentlemen born over it again: In which ſtately manner it was carried up to the Eaſt end of the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, and there placed in a magnificent Struc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture purpoſely erected there to receive it; being interred amongſt the Kings and Queens at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> for all which vaſt expences, his Son <hi>Richard</hi> might have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up that ſad expreſſion in <hi>Virgil.</hi> 
               <q>Infandum Regina jubes renovare dolorem.</q> had not the Parliament ſince dealt ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly with him, as to order the Payment of his Debs contracted by his Fathers Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. Certainly the Gentleman expreſſed noble and truly dutiful reſpects to his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, fit for brave Minds to imitate. Thus as great <hi>Oliver</hi> lived victoriouſly, ſo he was buried honourably, <hi>Sic Fxit.</hi> It was a report that his Effigies was taken down and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferved from a threatning Mulitude of the raſcally People; even he that had ſwayed and governed theſe three Nations five Years,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:54496:61"/>his Reign being troubleſome, was neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated after his Death to be protected in his Picture; his Poſterity after him being ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly levelled.</p>
            <p>Thus after many a weary Step, having traverſed ſo many Crowns, I muſt now ſet my Reader down at a Commonwealth. I ſhall end all with a Glimpſe rather than a Character, ſome gleaned Obſervations on this great Favourite of Fortune, I hope in Terms agreeing to Truth, ſuch as are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther below or above his Eſtate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="description">
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:54496:61"/>
            <head>THE <hi>CHARACTER,</hi> Or rather a GLYMPSE OF THIS <hi>Favourite</hi> of <hi>Fortune.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N his Perſon he ſomewhat exceeded the uſual middle Stature, proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable without any unevenneſs ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lineaments or parts, accordingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a becoming fatneſs, well ſhaped, his aſpect having ſomewhat of the Soldiers, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to redneſs, his uſual Poſture in his walking was his Hand upon his Sword; he had a ſparkling fierce Eye, nevertheleſs his uſual deportments were both courteous and harſh at once in his encounters, where he found the leaſt Oppoſition. He was hardy
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:54496:62"/>and reſolute in his reprehenſions, ſubtil, temperate, and meek in his Councils; he was of a ſtrong Conſtitution, and of an act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive Body, an Enemy both to eaſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; being ever ſuſpitious, circumſpect, and over vigiſant, of a notable Head-piece; yet if he had any ſpare time, he diſdained not to conſer though in matters of leaſt moment; he delighted to read Men more then Books, his eloquence being Maſculine and Martial, rather a natural Gift then an effect of Art, in which he did not want his holy Veſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, always managing ſome Paſſages of the ſacred Writ, to which moſt charming part (as well as that of the Sword) he owed moſt of his Victories. He was always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to exhort his Soldiers at the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of any great enterprize, or before a Battle: He had a ſtrict Eye over his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, his greateſt Care being to ſee them pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided of all Neceſſaries, by which Foreſight he was the better able to execute ſevere Puniſhment on them for their Miſdemean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. He took great Delight to diſcourſe of the Affairs of the World, of the Intereſts of other Princes, in which his Judgment did ſo guide him, that without entering into their Cabinets, or partaking of their ſecret Councils, he could diſcourſe very pertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of their Affairs, and foreſaw their ſeveral
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:54496:62"/>Iſſues and Events; he was an excellent Phyſiognomer, having once ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered any one, he was ſeldom deceived in the Opinion he had of him. He was no Friend to the vain-gloriouſneſs of Habit, and though he was always as it were fierce, of a paſſionate Conſtitution; yet he was ſo, ſly, as to keep his Paſſions in; but when there was Occaſion to carry a Buſineſs on he expoſed himſelf with ſo much Vigour, as gave thoſe he had to do withal to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that he was not eaſily perſwaded fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m the Thing he had once reſolved. He had one knack above all the reſt which ſtood him in much ſtead, he had a deep Inſight into the Natures and Diſpoſitions of the common People, who as they are impatient of Servitude, ſo are they incapable of intire Liberty; frighted with the Sight of the Rod, but mutinous in the feeling of it, none talking more of Liberty, nor underſtanding it leſs then they; more troubling themſelves then their Heads with their Grievances, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering nothing but repinining at every thing; bold Talkers ſo you ſuffer them but to talk: Above all, moſt tenacious of their Liberty of Conſcience, rather to follow any new fangled Opinion, then to remain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to the Old; his Policy herein was to allow them ſomething to induce others to
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:54496:63"/>their dear Liberty (or Lice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne rather) of their Tongues, which he knew he could not help, but ſo as that he had his Eves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dropp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs every where, who ſeldom brought him Word of what they ſaid, except they alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave an Account of what they had, and then their Eſtates paid for the malepertneſs of their Tongues, and for their chiefeſt dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of all to err in in their Opinions: He permitted them to follow and embrace what Sect they pleaſed, ſo that they all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in Obedience to Civil Government. This was his Method, whilſt Mens reaſons did comprehend ſo little, as that they needed their own experience to believe how he <hi>(Atlas-like)</hi> could ſupport ſo mighty a Frame and Machine, compoſed of ſo many different and disjoynted parts, yet to keep them from ſlipping and falling in pieces; which he did, rivetting them ſo faſt toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and making them all firmly cohere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, as ſo many Pieces of ſoft Wax melted and moulded all in one could not cleave faſter in a Ball or Globe; this was the great Work he had begun, which had not Death prevented him, he was on point of finiſhing, as he was a Perſon indefatigable both of Body and Mind.</p>
            <p>Politicians hold, that in the changing the Government, all things, if it were conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:54496:63"/>and poſſible, ought to be changed; the very Religion it ſelf, if any were prophane enough to meddle with it. To wave their Atheiſtical Opinions, this may be obſerved, that both in reſpect of his Policy and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, he might very well, having ſo many Advantages over the preſent Diſtractions of the Times, raiſe his Thoughts to more then ordinary Ambitions: It is only for God to ſearch the Heart, and try the Reins, he knows what our Religious Affections are, we ought to conjecture charitably of what we cannot determine; this we are certain of, he could ſo well ſee through ſuperſtition (as in theſe Times they term it) for his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Advantage, as that his political Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence could diſpence with more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tranſactions; nevertheleſs he was ſtill under the Priviledge of the Sanctuary, ſome of the Clergy, (as they have ever done) ſtuck cloſe to him, to raiſe him and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; whereas the late King undid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for the then flouriſhing Clergy, and they themſelves for him. 'Tis true, his Actions were complying with a military Soul, ſo that he had the leſs Leiſure to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute Caſes of Conſcience; only he might with the Emperor, as he did, cite Saint <hi>Paul, The Good that I would, I do not; but the Evil that I would not,, that I do; now if I do
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:54496:64"/>that I onld not, it is no more I that do it, but Sin that remains in me.</hi> The truth is, he made no haſte in the Settlement of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs, as he was too crafty to diſturb the powerful party, thoſe that were unſettled in their Opinions.</p>
            <p>As to his State Employments he took ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Oaths, which for the preſent might ſtand him in ſome ſtead, yet certainly they might have endangered him to much Loſs in his after enterprizes, which depended upon Faith. In his Youth I have heard he was ſo uncircumſpect, as not to riſe, experience having taught him in his latter Time Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom to repair himſelf, his better Fortune miraculouſly making up all his breaches; his Martial Spirit advancing him in Times as it were ſet apart for his deſigns, full of Mutations and rare Accidents; for it is with Times as it is with ways, with ſome they are up Hill, and with ſome they are down Hill; nor could he have made good his Footing, had he not been full of ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, of ſecret Thoughts, of ſerious Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, full of Notes and Memorials, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as he was well read in the Men of his Time; whom to employ, whom to reward, whom to enquire of, whom to beware of; what were the Dependancy, what were the Factions, as it were keeping a Journal of
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:54496:64"/>his Thoughts, Indeed one can ſcarcely write that he was too ſuſpicious. too appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive, though queſtionleſs he was by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his reſtleſs Jealouſies a trouble to himſelf as well as others, ſo that which did him good one Way, did him hurt another.</p>
            <p>Although, as hath been already ſaid, his Flies and Familiars were uſeful to him for the diſcovering of Conſpiracies, the reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which no Queſtion preſerved him from many Dangers from being attempted, his Nature being almoſt married to Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, his confidence made him ſucceſsful, to go through them; his cunning always wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him out, he being the more ready, and ſharpened by the Occaſions of Perils: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the dazelings of his ſuſpicions gave his Induſtries enough to do to ſave himſelf and help others. Queſtionleſs he had Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and a ſtrange kind of rule and ſtrain of Government, which all Men acknowledged in the bittereſt of Times. His Armies nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Civil nor Forreign Wars were ever unfortunate. As his great Judgment in lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as well as preſerving them, in Courage perſonally fighting with them, determined him to be both a daring Soldier, and an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Commander; which indeared his Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſo much to him, as that they ſuffered him to act for the future for himſelf what
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:54496:65"/>they did not ſo well diſguſt. Many Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles he fought with them, in all which he triumpht, his Fortunes being inviolable; thus as he appears ſtrangely ſucceſsful to Poſterity, ſo likewiſe moſt unhappy for thoſe bloody Conqueſts he obtained, they being in the Bowels of his own Country. He ſignalized the magnanimity of his Mind by putting his Soldiers on miraculous attempts, as well in the Chriſtian as the other Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Parts of the World; the Queſtion is, ſo much honourable Blood being ſhed in his time, whether future Hiſtories will waſh his Memory clean from it, tho' Malice it ſelf cannot charge him that he was actualy nocent, yet Poſterity will hardly believe but that he was in ſome degree guilty. But to come cloſer to him, of thoſe three Things which either ſhould or ought to tye the Hearts of the People to thoſe that govern, <hi>Love, Fear,</hi> and <hi>Reverence;</hi> he only purchaſt of them chiefly to himſelf <hi>Fear,</hi> which is furtheſt from the Heart; which forced him, being ſometimes ſtraitned in his Affairs, to retire much to his Cabinet Council, with whom he ſat often in Perſon, where he was always ſair ſpoken, not without his ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and blandiſhments of Words; but his Rhetorick was not ſo vainly ſpent, but that before he went he informed his Judgments;
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:54496:65"/>and tho' thoſe were cunning that he em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, yet he had ſtill a Reſerve to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, as he had the Maſter-reach; ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent his Judgment had, tho' it was not much aſſiſted by his former Learning, or bettered by his futune Studies; the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet and Drum ſounding ſo loud in his Ears, that he had little leiſure to admit of the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Councils of Philoſophy. He was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs well enough furniſht, as his Wit had long before purchaſed <hi>Lewis</hi> the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth's ſo well known ſlights, which he left to his Son as Maxims for his Practice, as one in another caſe writes of Secrets, that they ſhould be kept till the Breath ſtinks. Queſtionleſs his diſſimulation in Tranſactings, together with his Privacy and Silence in his Managements were to him Aſſiſtances beyond all Arts and Sciences. in his Time there were many that ſuffered the more Blood was drawn; the leſs Love he found, the leſs Treaſure, which with a good Will he never received. One writes, that he diſtributed forty thouſand Pounds a Year in charitable Uſes out of his own Purſe; he might have been more plain in his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, certainly he meant out of the Commonwealths Moneys. We may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude thus much, that his aunual Incomes were not ſo great as Malice hath given out,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:54496:66"/>conſidering all his neceſſary expences; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſpute they had been more inlarged, if the People had loved him but half ſo well as they fear'd him, tho' I muſt ſtill acknowledge it to be hard to diſtinguiſh of his Liberality, his Neceſſities having ſo much limited his Rewards; tho his Mind was high; and he purſued his own Way as one that always revered his own Will. If we look on his careful or rather politick Liberality, ſomewhat may be ſaid, as he was at vaſt Charges, as he made good his dexterity to impropriate himſelf with For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Inſtruments to obtain good Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence from all Parts abroad; from which Spies all wiſe Men conclude, that he receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more Articles of Inquiſition then Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as he was ſtill working and caſting up others, not to be undermined himſelf. Some are ſo humbly minded as to believe his Deſigns were to high for Forreign Parts, certain it is <hi>Carolus Guſtavus</hi> loſt a dear Friend of him; and for other Princes howſoever they might look a ſquint on him, he was courted by two of the greateſt, and was a Friend (as if Fortune attended him) to either of them both when he pleaſed, they having as much as they could allie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> themſelves to his Intereſts, when they on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> found him to be at leiſure to be helpful t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:54496:66"/>them. 'Tis true for ſome Time they ſtood at a diſtance, certainly if they did not ſo ſoon ſee into the Paſſages of his Affairs, they did at laſt paſs their Judgments on the Iſſue of them; perhaps they at the firſt ſaw him only at Strife, but they were afterwards forced to acknowledge him to be always a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loft, ſo fortunate he was in all his enterpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes. The Royal Party were once of Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that he having paſt his Laurels, he had a Mind to reach at the Crown; they were ſomewhat miſtaken, it had too many Thorns in it, which of themſelves are ſharp enough to fetch Blood, if we ſhould not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe accept of the Interpretation of the Fifth Monarchy Gentleman, who means by them the diſpleaſed Soldiery, to whom ſuch Luſtres could never have been acceptable, as ſome other of our late Pamphletters have libell'd him to be another <hi>Henry</hi> the Fifth, that he would have ſtolen the more then proteſted againſt Diadem off from the Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; if he had a Mind to it, it is more then they know, the worſt they could have ſaid of him had been, that he entertained ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more then ſelf-denying Thoughts, or rather as the Poets hath it, <hi>Magnis tamen ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit auſis.</hi> Indeed outwardly he ſeemed to have little of vain Glory in him, or elſe he turned his dark Lanthorn to himſelf, his
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:54496:67"/>cloſeneſs being always ſuch, that this great Politician walkt inviſible; others ſtood in the Light to him, but he in the Dark to all, only for his moſt grand Tranſaction there was no vizzard could diſguiſe it, that he ſhould after ſo many ſelfiſh refuſals, (a Word lately put into the new canting Dic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionary of the Enthuſiaſts) that he ſhould after the ſlighting as it were of ſo many ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, forfeited, and ſequeſtred Eſtates pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him by the Parliament for his remarkable Services; after that in parts and piecemeals he had denied the Pomps and Vanities of this wicked World, he made it his maſter-deſign to take in all at once, as he knew well enough how to cog a die, he had thrown for all, won all, and ſwept all at once; rendering his Motto, <hi>Pax quaeritur Bello,</hi> into that Engliſh which pleaſed him beſt, the Protectorſhip.</p>
            <p>To reflect briefly on his Domeſtical Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, he was not uxorious, but reſpectful to his Wife, to his Children he had a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal affection, careful of their educations, and of their aſpirings to advancement; he endeavoured to caſt a Luſtre on them, which did not take with the People, tho' as to his Son <hi>Richard</hi> there was a more then ordinary conſent. For his Pleaſures there is no extraordinary News of them, ſome
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:54496:67"/>Frolicks I have heard of, with thoſe he was moſt familiar, the Truth is, he had too little Leaſure for trivial repaſts; he did with them as great Perſons do with Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quers, come and look upon them, and ſo turn away. As he begun from a private Fortune, as I have already intimated, that Fortune quickened in him all Seeds of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, being always more proſperous in himſelf, then confirmed from the Affections of others. For the Imputations againſt him of Moneys in his Treaſury, certainly if he had been ſuch a hoarder, the Urgency of his preſſing Affairs would never ſuffer him to be ſo poor as to ſtand ſtill, and admire his Riches. Before I end, I cannot chuſe but remark his hard dealings with Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which he formerly ſo vindicated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the late King for his breach of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge about the five Members, whatſoever fine Thread he did twiſt for himſelf, in all his religious Speeches, thoſe that are right Engliſhmen will never clear him from his violations, tho' he managed thoſe actings as that they were to him but ſhort Tempeſts, or ſmall over-caſtings, as whatſoever Injury the Nations endured, he had one pretence or other to ſhift it off from his own Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, extreamly miſtaking himſelf, as the People look leſs on the failing of thoſe who
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:54496:68"/>have been their own choice, then on thoſe who have taken on them to be Carvers for themſelves; he thought himſelf crafty e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for Parliaments, and from his Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed he determined himſelf cock ſure, as he was fleſht with his former Fortunes; he could never have imagined his Poſterity ſhould ever have been lean. 'Tis true, we may be ſo political, as on this Earth to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to graſp theſe humane Affairs to our own Intereſts, but we muſt lay down our greateſt Wiſdoms when we come to ſleep in the ſilent Grave, as after Death there is no providing againſt the croſs blows of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
            <p>To conclude, as far as we can conjecture, his Confederates continuing alike victorious, and fortunate with him, he might i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he had lived to it, extended his Victories to ſome other parts of the World; if he did no more, it was either thro' the Diſturbances of the Times, or long of himſelf, for what he mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he compaſſed. Certain it is, that he ſo husbanded his ſucceſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that he did not live to ſee himſelf unfortunate, who having aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed or rather ſnacht his Honours, ſhewed himſelf to be one of the ſtrangeſt ſort of Wonders that our late Times have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb n="137" facs="tcp:54496:68"/>
            <head>One writ this ſtrange EPITAPH on Him.</head>
            <p>HERE LIES <hi>OLIVER CROMWEL,</hi> WHO THAT HE MIGHT BE PROTECTOR HIMSELF, FIRST BROUGHT THE ENGLISH MONARCHY ON ITS KNEEES.</p>
            <trailer>The <hi>END.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:54496:69"/>
            <head>A CATALOGUE of BOOKS Sold by DANIEL PRATT, at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in the <hi>Strand, London.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>ARiſtotle's Maſter Piece.</item>
               <item>The Art of Gardening.</item>
               <item>Anne of Bullen.</item>
               <item>An Accademy of Complements.</item>
               <item>Banquet for Ladies and Gentlemen.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bunyon</hi>'s Hearts Eaſe.</item>
               <item>The ſeven Champions.</item>
               <item>Cynthia.</item>
               <item>The French Convert.</item>
               <item>The ſeven Wiſe Maſters.</item>
               <item>The ſeven Wiſe Miſtreſſes.</item>
               <item>The Secretary's Guide.</item>
               <item>The Deſtruction of Troy.</item>
               <item>The Great Aſſize.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Francis Spira.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thomas Savage.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ruſſels</hi> Sermons.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s Famous Titles.</item>
               <item>Weeks Preparation.</item>
               <item>The nine Worthies.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54496:69"/>
The Pleaſures of Matrimony.</item>
               <item>Reynard the Fox.</item>
               <item>Aeſop's Fables.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pariſmus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Duty of a Woman.</item>
               <item>Guy of Warwick.</item>
               <item>The wonderful Prodiges:</item>
               <item>Wars in England.</item>
               <item>Mars and Venus.</item>
               <item>Nine Novels.</item>
               <item>The Wooden World.</item>
               <item>Winter Evenings Entertainments.</item>
               <item>Rocheſter's Poems.</item>
               <item>Ladies Delight.</item>
               <item>Duty of Sacrament.</item>
               <item>Triumph of Wit.</item>
               <item>Come and Welcome.</item>
               <item>Queens Cookery.</item>
               <item>Cry of the Son of God.</item>
               <item>Ariſtotle's Legacy.</item>
               <item>Ariſtotle's Problems.</item>
               <item>Token for Youth.</item>
               <item>Marriners Jewel.</item>
               <item>Cambridge Jeſts.</item>
               <item>Cabinet of Wit.</item>
               <item>Hiſtory of Montelion.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54496:70"/>
Gentlemans Jockey.</item>
               <item>Lambert of Cattle.</item>
               <item>Compleat Servant Maid.</item>
               <item>Hocus Pocus.</item>
               <item>Fortunatus.</item>
               <item>Poſie of Prayer.</item>
               <item>Culpeper's Midwife.</item>
               <item>French Rogue.</item>
               <item>Scholars Recreation.</item>
               <item>Flavel of the Sacrament.</item>
               <item>Grace Abounding.</item>
               <item>Pilgrim's Progreſs.</item>
               <item>Three Novels.</item>
               <item>Univerſal Jeſter.</item>
               <item>Royal Jeſter.</item>
               <item>Coffee-Houſe Jeſts.</item>
               <item>Female Policy.</item>
               <item>Oxford Jeſts.</item>
               <item>Lilly's Book of Fortune.</item>
               <item>Eſſex and Elizabeth.</item>
               <item>The Shepherds Kalender.</item>
               <item>War with the Devil.</item>
               <item>The merry Companion.</item>
               <item>Lydals Spelling Book.</item>
               <item>Cockers Spelling Book.</item>
               <item>Toungs Spelling Book.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54496:70"/>
Artimedorus of Dreams.</item>
               <item>Laugh and be Fat.</item>
               <item>Argalus and Parthenia.</item>
               <item>Valentine and Orſon.</item>
               <item>Duty of Prayer.</item>
               <item>Cocker's Arithmetick.</item>
               <item>Arts Treaſury.</item>
               <item>Ayre's Arithmetick.</item>
               <item>Arraignment of Women.</item>
               <item>The Art of Legerdemain.</item>
               <item>Bunyons Holy War.</item>
               <item>Solomons Temple.</item>
               <item>Sighs from Hell.</item>
               <item>The Book of Knowledge.</item>
               <item>Crucified Saviour.</item>
               <item>Crumbs of Comfort.</item>
               <item>Dyers Works.</item>
               <item>Divine Breathings.</item>
               <item>Engliſh Rogue.</item>
               <item>Female Grievances.</item>
               <item>Holy Jeſus.</item>
               <item>Wars of the Jews.</item>
               <item>Hiſtory of fair Roſamond.</item>
               <item>Hiſtory of the Tales of the Fairies.</item>
               <item>Harts Sermons.</item>
               <item>The Life of Oliver Cromwel.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54496:71"/>
Jacobs Ladder.</item>
               <item>Mother's Bleſſing.</item>
               <item>Travels of Godlineſs.</item>
               <item>Travels of Ungodlineſs.</item>
               <item>New Years Gift.</item>
               <item>Proteſtant Tutor.</item>
               <item>Practice of Piety.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pelling</hi> of Time.</item>
               <item>Quevedo's Viſions.</item>
               <item>Reynolds of Adultrey.</item>
               <item>Supplication of Saints.</item>
               <item>Secretary's Guide.</item>
               <item>Token for Marriners.</item>
               <item>Young Man's Calling.</item>
               <item>Art of Money Catching.</item>
               <item>The great Aſſize.</item>
               <item>Quakers Accademy.</item>
               <item>Young Mans Companion.</item>
               <item>Ladies Cloſet.</item>
               <item>Life of Robin Hood.</item>
               <item>Englands Monarchs.</item>
               <item>Robinſon Cruſo.</item>
               <item>Devout Communicant.</item>
               <item>Life of John Shepherd.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ious Breathings.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſtory of <hi>Jeoſephat.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:54496:71"/>
Devout Companion.</item>
               <item>Token for Children.</item>
            </list>
            <p>London, <hi>Printed by</hi> D. Pratt, <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Crown <hi>againſt</hi> York-Houſe, <hi>in the</hi> Strand. Where may be had all Chapmens Books, Bibles, Common-Prayers, and all ſorts of Stationary Wares.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="advert_for_medicine">
            <pb facs="tcp:54496:72"/>
            <p>THere is lately brought from <hi>Chili</hi> a Province in <hi>America,</hi> a moſt Natural Excellent <hi>Balſam,</hi> found by ſeveral Eminent Perſons to excel that of <hi>Peru</hi> and <hi>Tolu,</hi> in curing of divers Diſeaſes as it hath given de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration; 'tis a Remedy that no Man under the Sun can compoſe, being a moſt Odoriferous, and Natural Balſam. It cures moſt diſeaſes in human Bodies, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly helps, all Pains coming from cold, chiefly pains in the Stomach, want of Appetite, corroborating and ſtrengthning the whole Body. 'Tis a wonderful Remedy for all inward Sores, Bruiſes, Ulcers of the Lungs, Reins, Bladder or Womb, &amp;c. It helps ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Breath, Coughs, Conſumption or Wheeſings, 'tis good in moſt diſeaſes of the Head, as falling Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Appoplexy, Palſey, Trembling, Convulſions, Head Ach, and Giddineſs of the Head, and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens the Brain and Nerves: It kills the Worms and helps the Stone, and is a good provoker of Urine, and brings away the Sand and Gravel, which oftentimes Obſtructs the Urine; it helps all Fluxes of the Belly, and 'tis a wonderful thing for moſt Diſeaſes of the Ears, eſpecially Deaſneſs, and outwardly apply'd, cures all manner of green Wounds, Ulcers, and Fiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tula's, and cures moſt diſeaſes in Women, and many other Diſtempers, which you may ſee at large in the printed Bills of Direction.</p>
            <p>Whereas the <hi>Balſam</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Chili</hi> has been Sold by Mr. <hi>Eben Tracy,</hi> Bookſeller, at the <hi>Three Bibles</hi> on <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Bridge</hi> theſe 30 Years laſt paſt, but ſince his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, Mr: <hi>John Stuart</hi> Stationer at the <hi>Three Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bler</hi> and <hi>Ink Bottles,</hi> at the Corner of the <hi>Square</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>London Bridge,</hi> has made a ſham <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ort, which is an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Impoſition on the Publick, therefore the Buyers are deſir'd to take care that they come to the right Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note,</hi> The Right Sort is only to be had of <hi>John Tracy,</hi> at the <hi>Three Bibles</hi> on <hi>London Bridge,</hi> at one Shilling and Sixpence the Ounce: The Bottles are ſeal'd with the Balſam Eree.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:54496:72"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
